All righty.
알았어.
I believe it is time for us to kick this off.
이제 시작해야 할 때인 것 같아.
So we have so much to cover.
취재할 게 너무 많아요.
I'm going to go ahead and start.
제가 먼저 시작하죠.
Feel free to keep on coming if you're waiting in line.
줄을 서서 기다리시는 분들은 계속 오세요.
There's lots of seats up front here.
앞쪽에 자리가 많이 있습니다.
So yeah, welcome, welcome.
그래, 어서 오세요.
My name is Randy Abernathy.
제 이름은 랜디 애버나시입니다.
I'm a managing partner at RXM.
저는 RXM의 매니징 파트너입니다.
And this is Kubernetes Networking 101.
그리고 이것은 쿠버네티스 네트워킹 101입니다.
So let me just see a quick show of hands.
그럼 잠깐 손들어 보겠습니다.
How many people would consider themselves very savvy
자신을 매우 잘 안다고 생각하는 사람은 몇 명입니까?
networking people?
인맥을 쌓고 있나요?
All right.
알았어요.
So everybody else, if you saw someone raise their hand,
자, 다른 분들, 손 드신 분 손 들어 보세요,
you got questions.
질문이 있는 거죠.
You know where to go, right?
어디로 가야 할지 알지?
Those people.
저 사람들.
So yeah, this is going to be a super fun tutorial.
그래, 이건 정말 재미있는 튜토리얼이 될 거야.
We have 90 minutes.
90분 남았어요.
We have a ton of stuff to cover.
취재할 내용이 너무 많아요.
And I'll just give you a quick intro to the format.
형식에 대해 간단히 소개하겠습니다.
We have stood up hundreds of machines
우리는 수백 대의 기계를 세웠습니다.
in a cloud provider who shall remain nameless since they
클라우드 제공 업체에서 이름을 밝히지 않을 것입니다.
wouldn't sponsor us.
우리를 후원하지 않을 것입니다.
And so you guys can SSH into the box
이제 여러분은 상자에 SSH로 접속할 수 있습니다.
that you were provided on this sheet.
이 시트에 제공된 정보를 입력합니다.
Now, I realize that we're on conference Wi-Fi, right?
지금 우리가 회의용 Wi-Fi를 사용하고 있는 건 맞죠?
We all know what that means.
우리 모두 무슨 뜻인지 알죠?
It's probably really banging great Wi-Fi,
아마 와이파이가 정말 잘 터지는 것 같아요,
but there's 200, 300 people trying
하지만 200, 300명이 시도하고 있습니다.
to use it all at the same time.
동시에 사용하려고 합니다.
So the best thing that we could do
그래서 우리가 할 수 있는 최선의 방법은
is instead of you downloading all sorts of packages
모든 종류의 패키지를 다운로드하는 대신에
and containers and stuff that would be really slow,
정말 느릴 수 있는 컨테이너 같은 것들 말이죠,
you can just SSH to these cloud instances
이 클라우드 인스턴스에 SSH로 접속할 수 있습니다.
and send a few characters back and forth every once
그리고 한 번씩 몇 문자를 주고받을 수 있습니다.
in a while.
잠시 후
It's the lowest bandwidth thing that we can come up
우리가 올릴 수 있는 가장 낮은 대역폭입니다.
with for a session like this.
으로 설정할 수 있습니다.
It's also really great because if you completely
또한 다음과 같이 하면 정말 좋습니다.
thrash this computer, your laptop is still fine, right?
이 컴퓨터를 박살내도 노트북은 여전히 멀쩡하죠?
So don't worry, right?
그러니 걱정하지 마세요, 그렇죠?
It's a virtual machine.
가상 머신이니까.
And if you do completely thrash this computer, we have spares.
이 컴퓨터를 완전히 부숴버려도 여분이 있습니다.
So I have three folks helping me today, Chris, Ilian,
오늘은 크리스, 일리언, 세 사람이 도와줄 거예요,
and Valentin.
그리고 발렌틴.
And Chris is, by the way, doing a talk at 1600,
그리고 크리스는 1600시에 강연을 합니다,
Koop Koodle Said What, which is going to be super awesome.
쿠프 쿠들이 무슨 말을 했더라, 정말 멋질 거야.
So I would go to that if I were you.
나 같으면 저기로 갈 거야.
But those guys are going to come around and help with questions.
하지만 저 사람들이 와서 질문을 도와줄 거예요.
So if you have a question, raise your hand.
질문이 있으시면 손을 들어주세요.
Those guys will be scanning the room.
저 사람들이 방을 스캔할 겁니다.
They'll come to you.
그들이 당신에게 올 겁니다.
They can give you a new machine if you need it.
필요하면 새 기계를 줄 수 있습니다.
We got spares.
여분이 있습니다.
They can help you get unstuck if you're
다음과 같은 경우에 도움이 될 수 있습니다.
working on a part of the tutorial that isn't working.
튜토리얼의 작동하지 않는 부분을 작업 중입니다.
We've tested it a bunch of times,
여러 번 테스트했습니다,
so I feel pretty good about if you read the tutorial steps
그래서 튜토리얼 단계를 읽으면 꽤 괜찮을 것 같습니다.
carefully and do them the way that they say,
주의 깊게 살펴보고 시키는 대로 하세요,
it's going to work.
잘 될 거야.
So hopefully, we won't have too many problems.
큰 문제는 없겠지?
But we're here to help.
하지만 우리가 도와줄게요.
If you have any questions at all, feel free to ask.
궁금한 점이 있으면 언제든지 문의하세요.
Yeah, question?
네, 질문 있으세요?
Is it possible to get a phone for a laptop?
노트북용 전화기를 구할 수 있나요?
노트북용 휴대폰을 구할 수 있나요?
Ah, great question.
아, 좋은 질문이네요.
So when we get to the first lab break,
이제 첫 번째 실험실 쉬는 시간에 도착했습니다,
I'll go into this in some more detail.
좀 더 자세히 설명하겠습니다.
But the question was, hey, I don't have my laptop,
그런데 문제는 제 노트북이 없다는 거죠,
or my laptop's locked down, or something,
아니면 노트북이 잠겼거나 뭐 그런 거죠,
and I can't get to these boxes.
이 상자에 접근할 수 없어요.
What do I do?
어떻게 해야 하나요?
Well, we're going to have some slides and presentation.
슬라이드와 프레젠테이션을 준비할게요.
And I'll probably do a lot of the steps
그리고 아마 많은 단계를 할 거예요.
if I have time while I'm running around, so you get to see that.
제가 뛰어다니는 동안 시간이 나면요, 보실 수 있습니다.
But also, there's instructions in the lab
실험실에는 다음과 같은 지침도 있습니다.
as to how to stand up a plain vanilla Ubuntu 2004 server
일반 바닐라 우분투 2004 서버를 세우는 방법에 대한 설명입니다.
that you can do the labs on.
실험을 할 수 있습니다.
There's nothing special about these labs.
이 실험실에는 특별한 것이 없습니다.
They're just running on a plain vanilla Ubuntu 2004 server.
그냥 평범한 바닐라 우분투 2004 서버에서 실행 중입니다.
We literally start from the absolute start,
말 그대로 절대적인 시작에서 시작합니다,
install Kubernetes, set up CNI, start
쿠버네티스를 설치하고, CNI를 설정하고, 시작한다.
creating services, install the service mesh,
서비스를 생성하고, 서비스 메시를 설치한다,
install the ingress.
인그레스를 설치합니다.
Everything is right in that lab.
실험실에 모든 것이 정상입니다.
So it'll be really easy to redo later.
나중에 다시 하기가 정말 쉬울 거야.
Also, and I appreciate that question,
그리고 질문 고마워요,
because hello, virtual people.
안녕, 가상의 사람들아.
All the people who are over here, hello, virtual people.
여기 있는 모든 사람들아, 안녕, 가상의 사람들아.
All the people who are online, obviously, you
온라인에 있는 모든 사람들, 당연히 여러분.
didn't get one of these sheets with an IP.
이 시트에 IP가 있는 사람은 없습니다.
We just, there's like 800 people or something signed up,
800명 정도 가입한 것 같아요,
so we couldn't do it for everybody.
그래서 모두를 위해 해줄 수는 없었어요.
But if you've got a box that you can use that's
하지만 사용할 수 있는 상자가 있으면
a plain vanilla Ubuntu box, a VM,
일반 바닐라 우분투 박스, 가상머신,
you can just either SSH into that.
그냥 SSH로 접속하면 됩니다.
If it's in a data center, it's on your laptop.
데이터 센터에 있다면 노트북에 있는 것입니다.
If it's in a cloud somewhere, that's going to work fine.
클라우드 어딘가에 있다면 정상적으로 작동할 것입니다.
And there are instructions for doing exactly that in the lab.
실험실에 정확히 그렇게 하는 방법이 있습니다.
The lab points you to a virtual machine setup
실습에서 가상 머신 설정으로 이동합니다.
doc, which is a markdown on GitHub.
문서로 이동합니다.
And you can follow the instructions there
그리고 거기에 있는 지침을 따를 수 있습니다.
to run a basic VM that we already provided for you.
이미 제공한 기본 가상 머신을 실행할 수 있습니다.
It's just a plain vanilla Ubuntu box again.
다시 평범한 바닐라 우분투 박스입니다.
But you can stand that up and do the labs.
그래도 견디고 실험을 할 수 있겠지.
So yeah, great questions.
그래, 좋은 질문이네.
And I'll continue to give you more information about the lab
그리고 실험실에 대한 자세한 정보를 계속 알려드리겠습니다.
as we close in on getting started on the first step.
첫 번째 단계의 시작이 가까워지고 있습니다.
This session is organized into five parts.
이 세션은 다섯 부분으로 구성되어 있습니다.
We're going to take about 15 minutes for each part.
각 파트당 약 15분 정도 소요됩니다.
And then I've got a very tight budget here to get started.
예산이 매우 빠듯해서 시작하기가 어렵네요.
So we're going to do maybe five minutes of discussion
그럼 5분 정도 토론을 해보겠습니다.
and then 10 minutes of lab work, five minutes of discussion,
10분간 실험하고 5분간 토론하는 거죠,
10 minutes of lab work.
10분간 실험실 작업.
This is a hands-on session.
실습 세션입니다.
This is a tutorial.
튜토리얼입니다.
So you're going to be doing all of this stuff.
이 모든 것을 해보겠습니다.
And I'm only going to give you the overview
개요만 알려드리겠습니다.
because you're going to do it.
네가 할 거니까.
Why should I tell you the commands
명령을 알려줘야 하는 이유
when you're going to type them yourself?
직접 입력할 건데?
So all right, so that's it.
자, 이제 끝났습니다.
So these three guys are out there ready to help.
이 세 사람이 도와줄 준비가 됐군요.
Also, you'll see that there is a tutorial lab doc
또한 튜토리얼 랩 문서가 있습니다.
in the slide deck here.
가 있습니다.
It's also on your sheet.
시트에도 있습니다.
So for the virtual people, you can get this deck off Skedge.
가상의 사람들을 위해, 이 덱을 스케지에서 가져올 수 있습니다.
So these slides are on Skedge already.
이 슬라이드는 이미 스케지에 있습니다.
So if you go to the talk, you see the schedule,
강연으로 이동하면 일정이 표시됩니다,
you know, the slide link, click that, you'll get this doc.
슬라이드 링크를 클릭하시면 이 문서를 보실 수 있습니다.
And then that link will take you to the markdown.
그리고 그 링크를 클릭하면 마크다운으로 이동합니다.
So let me just preview that markdown for you real quick,
이제 마크다운을 빠르게 미리 보여드리겠습니다,
make sure everybody is able to find it.
모든 사람이 찾을 수 있는지 확인합니다.
It looks like this.
이렇게 보입니다.
All right, so if you follow this GitHub link,
자, 이 깃허브 링크를 따라가면,
it takes you to KubeCon EU 2022.
KubeCon EU 2022로 이동합니다.
So the full URL is github.com slash RX dash M
따라서 전체 URL은 github.com 슬래시 RX 대시 M입니다.
slash KubeCon dash EU dash 2022 slash tree slash main,
슬래시 큐브콘 대시 EU 대시 2022 슬래시 트리 슬래시 메인,
obviously.
분명히.
And then if you click on the markdown,
그리고 마크다운을 클릭합니다,
it's just gonna open right up.
바로 열립니다.
That's the lab, right?
저기가 실험실 맞죠?
And you'll notice that it's broken up into steps.
단계별로 나뉘어져 있는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So step one, our first lab session
1단계, 첫 번째 실습 세션
is gonna be pod networking.
포드 네트워킹입니다.
And that doc's not going anywhere.
그리고 그 문서는 아무데도 가지 않을 겁니다.
That'll be there forever.
저건 영원히 저기 있을 거야.
So you can look at that in three years if you want to.
원한다면 3년 후에도 볼 수 있어요.
Nothing will work, I'm sure, but you can try it.
효과가 있을지는 모르겠지만 시도해 볼 수는 있겠지.
Okay, so that's a bit of the startup.
좋아, 이제 시작이네요.
Hopefully now everybody's got a sheet with the IP.
이제 모두들 IP가 적힌 시트를 받았겠지?
The other thing you're gonna need to log into the lab system
실험실 시스템에 로그인하려면 또 하나 필요한 게 있습니다.
you need an IP address to reach the host,
호스트에 접속하려면 IP 주소가 필요합니다,
and then you need to prove your identity.
그리고 신원을 증명해야 합니다.
And so you're gonna be Ubuntu, big surprise, right?
그래서 당신은 우분투가 되는 거군요, 놀랍지 않나요?
That's your user ID.
그게 네 사용자 아이디야.
And then you're gonna need a key.
그리고 키가 필요합니다.
And that key, the link for the key is on here too.
그 열쇠, 열쇠 링크도 여기 있습니다.
So here's a hint also, it's the same key.
여기에도 같은 키가 있다는 힌트가 있습니다.
So if somebody needs help,
누군가 도움이 필요하다면
you can log into their machine, right?
그들의 컴퓨터에 로그인할 수 있죠?
These machines are all going away in about two hours.
이 기계들은 약 2시간 후에 모두 사라질 거예요.
So, all right, that's enough of the logistics.
자, 물류는 여기까지입니다.
Let's talk about the talk.
대화에 대해 얘기해보죠.
So our goal is to introduce the world of Kubernetes
우리의 목표는 쿠버네티스의 세계를 소개하는 것이다.
network communications in a high level but practical way.
네트워크 통신을 높은 수준이지만 실용적인 방식으로 소개하는 것이다.
The idea of each of these little thought experiments,
이 작은 사고 실험의 아이디어들,
these little labs is to show you how a part
이 작은 실험들은 부품이 어떻게 작동하는지 보여주기 위한 것입니다.
of the Kubernetes networking world works in enough depth
쿠버네티스 네트워킹 세계의 일부가 어떻게 작동하는지 충분히 깊이 있게 보여준다.
that you understand it and you could walk away and go, cool.
이해했으니 이제 그만 가도 된다.
I'm not a networking person, but now I get it.
저는 인맥을 쌓는 사람은 아니지만 이제 알겠어요.
And everything's gonna be a lot easier for me
이제 모든 게 훨씬 쉬워질 거예요.
because I understand all these little parts.
이 모든 작은 부분들을 이해하니까요.
Or if you are interested in digging deeper,
또는 더 깊이 파고들고 싶다면,
you have a beginning point, right?
시작점이 있죠?
We've installed all the stuff, everything works together.
모든 것을 설치했고, 모든 것이 함께 작동합니다.
That's a lot of the times, you know, the big time waster.
시간 낭비인 경우가 많아요.
Now you can get down to the business of playing with it
이제 본업으로 돌아가서 놀아도 돼요.
and experimenting and taking your journey further.
실험하고 더 멀리 나아갈 수 있습니다.
So that's the idea behind this session.
이것이 이번 세션의 주제입니다.
Concepts and projects that we're gonna explore,
우리가 탐구할 개념과 프로젝트,
we're gonna begin with container networking
컨테이너 네트워킹부터 시작하겠습니다.
and talk about pods and how they talk together.
그리고 파드와 파드가 함께 대화하는 방법에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
And that is gonna involve a CNI plugin.
그리고 여기에는 CNI 플러그인이 포함될 것이다.
Kubernetes doesn't, it's not opinionated, right?
쿠버네티스는 그렇지 않죠?
It doesn't come with a networking solution.
네트워킹 솔루션이 제공되지 않습니다.
It doesn't come with a container runtime.
컨테이너 런타임이 제공되지 않습니다.
It doesn't come with storage drivers, right?
스토리지 드라이버가 제공되지 않나요?
You have to add all those in
여기에 모두 추가해야 합니다.
through the container network interface,
를 추가해야 합니다,
the container runtime interface
컨테이너 런타임 인터페이스
and the container storage interface, right?
그리고 컨테이너 스토리지 인터페이스, 맞죠?
Those are the three big legs of the Kubernetes stool.
이것이 쿠버네티스 스툴의 세 개의 큰 다리이다.
It's very rare to find a Kubernetes cluster
쿠버네티스 클러스터를 찾는 것은 매우 드물다.
that doesn't have plugins for all three of those
이 세 가지 모두에 대한 플러그인이 없는 쿠버네티스 클러스터는 거의 없다.
and sometimes multiple plugins for some of them.
그리고 때로는 일부에 대해 여러 개의 플러그인이 있습니다.
But to just get up and running,
하지만 일단 시작하고 실행해 보세요,
after you've installed Kubernetes,
쿠버네티스를 설치한 후,
you're gonna need a container network interface plugin
컨테이너 네트워크 인터페이스 플러그인이 필요하다.
and we're gonna use Cilium.
그리고 실리움을 사용하겠습니다.
Cilium is a project at the CNCF,
실리움은 CNCF의 프로젝트입니다,
really cool solution for networking.
네트워킹을 위한 정말 멋진 솔루션입니다.
We'll talk about that briefly.
잠시만요.
Then we're gonna get into step two,
그럼 2단계로 넘어가겠습니다,
which is Kubernetes services.
쿠버네티스 서비스입니다.
So once we've got our cluster running
클러스터가 실행되고 나면
and we've got the network in place
네트워크가 준비되면
and we've seen how it works
어떻게 작동하는지 확인했습니다.
and understand the absolute basics,
그리고 절대적인 기본을 이해합니다,
we're gonna dig into services
서비스를 파헤치겠습니다.
and we're gonna see how services give us a front end
서비스가 어떻게 우리에게 프런트엔드를 제공하는지 살펴볼 것입니다.
for a set of dynamically changing pods.
동적으로 변경되는 파드 집합에 대해.
Clients don't want the heartburn
클라이언트는 속쓰림을 원하지 않습니다.
of figuring out who to connect to.
누구와 연결할지 고민하고 있습니다.
They want a virtual IP address
가상 IP 주소를 원합니다.
that they can look up by name,
이름으로 조회할 수 있는 가상 IP 주소를 원합니다,
that they just connect to and then the magic happens
연결하기만 하면 마법이 일어납니다.
and they get to one of the pods, right?
포드 중 하나에 도착하는 거죠?
So that's what services are all about.
이것이 바로 서비스입니다.
We're gonna look at how Kubernetes does that,
쿠버네티스가 이를 어떻게 수행하는지 살펴보겠습니다,
at least one of the ways that it does it.
적어도 한 가지 방법을 살펴보자.
And then we're gonna take a look at DNS.
그리고 DNS를 살펴보겠습니다.
Humans don't like to remember IP addresses.
사람은 IP 주소를 기억하는 것을 좋아하지 않습니다.
Also, IP addresses tend to change a lot more than concepts.
또한 IP 주소는 개념보다 훨씬 더 많이 바뀌는 경향이 있습니다.
A service name is a concept.
서비스 이름은 개념입니다.
If you have a CFO reporting service,
CFO 보고 서비스가 있는 경우,
it's probably gonna be called CFO reporting forever
아마 영원히 CFO 리포팅이라고 불릴 겁니다.
or for a very long time and anywhere you put it.
아니면 아주 오랫동안, 어디에 두든.
But if you deploy that in Singapore,
하지만 싱가포르에 배포한다면,
it's gonna have one IP.
하나의 IP를 갖게 됩니다.
If you deploy that in London, it's gonna have another IP.
런던에 배포하면 다른 IP를 갖게 됩니다.
So services use these names to create an abstraction,
따라서 서비스는 이러한 이름을 사용하여 추상화를 생성합니다,
again, another level of abstraction
다시, 또 다른 수준의 추상화
on top of that virtual IP
그 가상 IP 위에
and we're gonna see how Kubernetes implements DNS
그리고 쿠버네티스가 DNS를 구현하는 방법을 살펴보자.
and it does it in some interesting and creative ways.
그리고 몇 가지 흥미롭고 창의적인 방식으로 이를 수행한다.
One thing that's fundamental
기본이 되는 한 가지
that we're gonna hammer on a little bit
우리가 조금 망치질 거라는 것.
are concepts around Kubernetes.
는 쿠버네티스를 둘러싼 개념이다.
You'll never understand Kubernetes networking
쿠버네티스 네트워킹을 절대 이해하지 못할 것이다.
if you don't understand Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스를 이해하지 못한다면.
Kubernetes thinks about the world a certain way.
쿠버네티스는 세상을 특정한 방식으로 생각한다.
You don't have to deploy applications that way.
애플리케이션을 그런 식으로 배포할 필요는 없다.
But if you don't understand it,
하지만 이해하지 못한다면,
you're gonna keep stepping into potholes.
계속 움푹 파인 곳을 밟게 될 거야.
If you understand it, you can protect yourself and say,
만약 당신이 그것을 이해한다면, 당신은 자신을 보호하고 말할 수 있습니다,
well, Kubernetes wants this to be this way,
쿠버네티스는 이렇게 되기를 원한다,
but we're gonna change it a little bit
하지만 우리는 그것을 조금 변경할 것이다.
and we're gonna make sure we've done the correct things
그리고 우리가 올바른 일을 했는지 확인할 거야.
to keep Kubernetes happy when we do it slightly differently
약간 다르게 할 때 쿠버네티스를 만족시킬 수 있다.
from how Kubernetes expects.
쿠버네티스가 기대하는 방식과 다르다.
And this really applies to networking
그리고 이것은 네트워킹에 실제로 적용된다.
and we're gonna see some of this in the DNS section.
그리고 DNS 섹션에서 이 중 일부를 볼 수 있습니다.
Next, we're gonna do step four, which is outside access.
다음으로 4단계인 외부 액세스를 수행합니다.
We're gonna see how from a cluster
클러스터에서 어떻게 하는지 보겠습니다.
where you've got all your cool services running,
모든 멋진 서비스가 실행되는 곳입니다,
you can get from the outside in
외부에서 들어올 수 있는
and there's a lot of ways to do that,
그리고 그 방법에는 여러 가지가 있습니다,
but fundamentally, there's two simple paths
하지만 근본적으로 두 가지 간단한 경로가 있습니다.
and there's lots of other crazy stuff
그리고 다른 많은 미친 것들이 있습니다.
that people are marketing and trying to tell you,
사람들이 마케팅하고 당신에게 말하려고 하는 것들,
there's two paths.
두 가지 경로가 있습니다.
Under the covers of all these things, there's two ways in.
이 모든 것의 이면에는 두 가지 길이 있습니다.
And so we're gonna look at that
그래서 우리는 그것을 살펴볼 것입니다.
and we're gonna talk about some of the cool projects
그리고 몇 가지 멋진 프로젝트에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
that fit in there.
저기에 들어갈 수 있을 것 같네요.
In addition to core DNS on the DNS side,
DNS 측의 코어 DNS에 추가됩니다,
we're gonna look at emissary for ingress
우리는 침입을 위해 엠시저를 살펴볼 것입니다.
and gateway kinds of functions.
그리고 게이트웨이 종류의 기능들을 살펴보겠습니다.
Envoy is a proxy that emissary uses under the covers.
Envoy는 사절이 은밀하게 사용하는 프록시입니다.
And then we're gonna look at,
그리고 나서 살펴볼게요,
well, we're gonna talk about Metal LB.
메탈 LB에 대해 얘기해볼게요.
Sometimes when we do this talk, we run Metal LB,
가끔 이 강연을 할 때 메탈 LB를 실행합니다,
but with this many people, it would be crazy.
하지만 이렇게 많은 사람이 모이면 미친 짓이죠.
So we're not gonna do that.
그러니 안 할 거야.
But we'll talk about it a little bit.
하지만 조금 후에 얘기하자.
And then finally, we're gonna get into service mesh,
그리고 마지막으로 서비스 메시를 살펴보겠습니다,
step five, this is sort of the pinnacle, right?
5단계, 이게 정점이죠?
After you've got everything else working perfectly,
다른 모든 것이 완벽하게 작동하면,
that's when you might wanna start thinking
그때부터 생각하기 시작할 수 있습니다.
about service mesh.
서비스 메시입니다.
Not everybody needs a service mesh.
모든 사람에게 서비스 메시가 필요한 것은 아닙니다.
I don't buy that.
난 안 믿어.
Not everybody needs a service mesh.
모든 사람에게 서비스 메시가 필요한 것은 아닙니다.
However, a service mesh is an incredibly powerful
하지만 서비스 메시가 매우 강력하다면
and valuable thing and so you might need it,
가치 있는 것이므로 필요할 수도 있습니다,
you might want it.
당신이 원할지도 모릅니다.
It can be an incredibly valuable tool.
엄청나게 가치 있는 도구가 될 수 있습니다.
We're gonna talk about what service meshes do
서비스 메시가 하는 일에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
and we're gonna use the only graduated project
그리고 유일하게 눈금이 매겨진 프로젝트를 사용하겠습니다.
in the CNCF ecosystem that is a service mesh, LinkerD.
서비스 메시인 링커D를 사용할 것입니다.
And it's a super cool project,
정말 멋진 프로젝트입니다,
has a ton of amazing features
놀라운 기능들이 많아요
and we'll just scratch the surface in this session.
이번 세션에서는 그 중 일부만 살펴보겠습니다.
But you'll have it installed,
하지만 설치는 할 수 있을 겁니다,
you'll see how easy it is to fire up
부팅이 얼마나 쉬운지 알 수 있습니다.
and you'll know the basics so you can, again,
그리고 기본을 알게 되므로 다시 할 수 있습니다,
carry on your journey and explore LinkerD all you want
여정을 계속하고 원하는 대로 LinkerD를 탐색하세요.
after the fact.
애프터 더 팩트.
Okay, so that is our plan.
좋아, 이게 우리 계획이야.
Now let's see how we do.
이제 어떻게 되는지 봅시다.
I'm gonna quickly switch over here.
여기로 빨리 전환할게요.
We have burned 10 minutes.
10분이 소모되었습니다.
Yikes, okay, we gotta get going.
이런, 이제 가야겠어.
All right, so step one.
좋아, 1단계.
And remember, if you've got questions,
그리고 궁금한 게 있으면 물어보세요,
there's three guys, right?
남자가 세 명이지?
Chris, Ilian, and Valentin out here that will help you out.
크리스, 일리안, 발렌틴이 당신을 도와줄 거예요.
So just raise your hand and they'll come
손만 들면 그들이 올 거야.
and answer your questions while I keep going
제가 계속 진행하는 동안 질문에 대답해 주세요
to keep us on track.
계속 진행합니다.
All right, so container networking concepts.
자, 컨테이너 네트워킹 개념입니다.
Let's talk about this just briefly.
잠깐만 얘기해보죠.
The first thing I wanna say is there's no such thing
먼저 말씀드리고 싶은 건, 그런 건 없다는 겁니다.
as a container.
컨테이너로.
Maybe that's a little shocking
조금 충격적일 수도 있겠네요.
in a container-based convention,
컨테이너 기반 컨벤션에서,
but there really isn't, right?
하지만 실제로는 없지 않나요?
The Linux kernel has C groups.
리눅스 커널에는 C 그룹이 있습니다.
What do they do?
무엇을 할까요?
They are control groups.
그들은 대조군입니다.
They control how much memory or CPU you can use.
사용할 수 있는 메모리 또는 CPU의 양을 제어합니다.
The Linux kernel has namespaces.
리눅스 커널에는 네임스페이스가 있습니다.
What do they do?
무엇을 할까요?
They isolate what your process can see.
프로세스가 볼 수 있는 것을 격리합니다.
Can your process only see itself and its children
프로세스가 자신과 그 자식만 볼 수 있는지
or can it see the PIDs of other processes?
아니면 다른 프로세스의 PID를 볼 수 있습니까?
That's the PID namespace.
이것이 PID 네임스페이스입니다.
But what we care about is the network namespace.
하지만 우리가 신경 쓰는 것은 네트워크 네임스페이스입니다.
A network namespace makes it so that a process
네트워크 네임스페이스는 프로세스가 다음과 같이 되도록 합니다.
can have its own virtual copy of the IP stack.
프로세스가 IP 스택의 자체 가상 복사본을 가질 수 있도록 합니다.
Inside what we think of as a container,
우리가 컨테이너라고 생각하는 것의 내부,
you have your own route table, your own IP tables,
자체 경로 테이블과 자체 IP 테이블이 있습니다,
your own interfaces, loopback and things like that.
자체 인터페이스, 루프백 등이 있습니다.
So that's really useful because now we can reliably deploy
이제 안정적으로 배포할 수 있기 때문에 정말 유용합니다.
things that listen on port 80 many, many times
포트 80에서 여러 번 수신 대기하는 것들을
on the same computer because they all have
모두 같은 컴퓨터에서
their own interfaces.
인터페이스를 가지고 있기 때문입니다.
So this is magic, right?
이게 바로 마법이지?
If we had a big cluster of machines and we wanted
만약 우리가 큰 기계 클러스터를 가지고 있고, 우리가 원한다면
to dynamically roll out applications,
를 사용하여 애플리케이션을 동적으로 롤아웃할 수 있습니다,
they're all fighting for ports and craziness like that,
다들 포트와 그런 미친 짓을 위해 싸우고 있죠,
that would be pretty tough.
꽤나 힘들겠지.
So what ends up happening with container tech is
컨테이너 기술에서 결국 일어나는 일은
you get reliable deployment.
안정적인 배포가 가능합니다.
That's a really huge thing.
정말 대단한 일이죠.
But we need something to sort of do the deployment, right?
하지만 배포를 하려면 뭔가가 필요하겠죠?
To make the deployment work
배포를 하려면
and that's where Kubernetes comes in.
이것이 바로 쿠버네티스가 필요한 이유입니다.
And Kubernetes, there's no such thing as a container.
그리고 쿠버네티스에는 컨테이너라는 것이 없습니다.
What Kubernetes does is it takes container images,
쿠버네티스가 하는 일은 컨테이너 이미지를 가져오는 것이다,
which are just little tarballs with root file systems in them
루트 파일 시스템이 들어있는 작은 타르볼에 불과하다.
and it runs several of them in the same network namespace.
그리고 동일한 네트워크 네임스페이스에서 여러 개를 실행합니다.
That bundle is called a pod, right?
이 번들을 파드라고 하지?
They share the network namespace.
이들은 네트워크 네임스페이스를 공유한다.
They also share the interprocess communications namespace.
프로세스 간 통신 네임스페이스도 공유합니다.
We want it to be cheap for them to talk to each other, right?
서로 대화하는 데 비용이 적게 들었으면 좋겠지?
So if you're using MQs or shared memory, stuff like that,
그래서 MQ나 공유 메모리 같은 걸 사용한다면요,
those are in the IPC namespace.
이 IPC 네임스페이스에 있습니다.
And if you're using the local loopback and stuff like that,
로컬 루프백 등을 사용하는 경우,
that's in the network namespace.
이 네트워크 네임스페이스에 있습니다.
So pods are collections of container images
따라서 파드는 컨테이너 이미지의 모음이다.
that are all running in shared network namespaces.
모두 공유 네트워크 네임스페이스에서 실행되고 있다.
So in Kubernetes, interestingly,
쿠버네티스에서는 흥미롭게도,
the pod is the unit of distribution.
파드는 배포 단위이다.
It's the smallest thing you can schedule.
스케줄링할 수 있는 가장 작은 단위입니다.
It's the smallest thing that you can scale
확장할 수 있는 가장 작은 단위입니다.
and they're atomic.
그리고 원자 단위입니다.
You can't run part of it on one machine
한 컴퓨터에서 일부를 실행할 수 없습니다.
and part of it on another, right?
일부는 다른 컴퓨터에서 실행할 수 없죠?
So really what we're thinking about
그래서 정말 우리가 생각하는 것은
when we move to Kubernetes is not container networking,
쿠버네티스로 이동할 때 컨테이너 네트워킹이 아니다,
it's pod networking.
파드 네트워킹이다.
And so pod networking works like this.
파드 네트워킹은 이렇게 작동한다.
You have an interface in one pod
하나의 파드에 인터페이스가 있다.
and an interface in another pod.
다른 파드에 인터페이스가 있다.
They both have IP addresses and now you can talk, right?
둘 다 IP 주소가 있고 이제 대화가 가능하죠?
These two guys can communicate with each other
이 두 사람은 서로 통신할 수 있습니다.
and you can have as many containers as you like
컨테이너를 원하는 만큼 가질 수 있습니다.
in the first pod and as many containers as you like
첫 번째 파드에서 원하는 만큼의 컨테이너를 가질 수 있다.
in the second pod or as few as you like.
두 번째 파드에 또는 원하는 만큼의 컨테이너.
So pods are the unit of distribution
따라서 파드는 배포 단위입니다.
and also the unit of network identity, right?
그리고 네트워크 아이덴티티의 단위이기도 하죠?
The unit of networking, they have an IP address.
네트워크의 단위인 IP 주소가 있습니다.
Interestingly enough, the pods need to be able
흥미롭게도, 파드는 다음을 수행할 수 있어야 한다.
to communicate with each other.
서로 통신할 수 있어야 한다.
That's what Kubernetes says.
이것이 쿠버네티스가 말하는 것이다.
All pods in a Kubernetes cluster
쿠버네티스 클러스터의 모든 파드
must be able to communicate with each other, right?
서로 통신할 수 있어야 하지 않나?
Now the world's changing.
이제 세상은 변하고 있어요.
There's lots of exceptions to the rule,
규칙에는 많은 예외가 있습니다,
but as far as your basic network requirements
하지만 기본적인 네트워크 요구 사항은
for Kubernetes to function the way that it's supposed to,
이 되어야 쿠버네티스가 정상적으로 작동한다,
all the pods have to be able to talk to each other.
모든 파드가 서로 통신할 수 있어야 한다.
Now what if I want to put some pods
이제 파드를 몇 개 넣으려면 어떻게 해야 하나요?
in the staging namespace and I don't want them
스테이징 네임스페이스에 넣고 싶지 않은데
talking to pods in the production namespace?
프로덕션 네임스페이스에서 파드와 대화하고 있는가?
Well, you can create network policies
네트워크 정책을 만들 수 있다.
that change the rules up and stuff,
규칙을 변경할 수 있습니다,
but it has to be possible for every pod
하지만 모든 파드에서 가능해야 한다.
to talk to every other pod.
다른 모든 파드와 대화할 수 있어야 한다.
What that means is that pods need to be able
이는 파드가 다음을 수행할 수 있어야 한다는 것을 의미한다.
to communicate with each other
서로 통신할 수 있어야 한다.
when they're on different machines.
서로 다른 컴퓨터에 있을 때.
Linux has stuff built into it, like Linux Bridge
리눅스에는 리눅스 브리지와 같은 기능이 내장되어 있습니다.
and things like that, that acts like a virtual switch
가상 스위치처럼 작동하는 것들이 있습니다.
where all the pods can talk to each other
모든 파드가 서로 대화할 수 있다.
and you don't really need any extra software.
추가 소프트웨어가 필요하지 않습니다.
But as soon as you start communicating
하지만 통신을 시작하자마자
outside of the computer to another computer,
컴퓨터 외부에서 다른 컴퓨터와 통신합니다,
something's gotta happen, right?
무슨 일이 일어나겠지?
Because these pods, in the old days,
왜냐면 이 포드들은, 옛날에,
we might put a piece of software on there
소프트웨어 조각을 넣을 수 있다.
and then we might go and program the network awhile
그리고 나서 네트워크를 잠시 프로그래밍할 수도 있습니다.
and now everybody knows where it is.
이제 다들 어디 있는지 알겠지.
That's not gonna fly in Kubernetes, right,
쿠버네티스에서는 안 되겠지?
where we're deploying nine times a day, 10 times a day,
하루에 9번, 하루에 10번씩 배포하는 곳입니다,
pods are scaling up and scaling down all day long.
파드가 하루 종일 스케일업 및 스케일다운되고 있다.
That's not gonna fly, it's gotta be automated.
저건 날아가지 않을 거야, 자동화해야 해.
So we need software to find networking.
네트워킹을 찾으려면 소프트웨어가 필요해.
But the problem is if Kubernetes just said,
하지만 문제는 쿠버네티스가 방금 말한 것처럼,
yeah, supply some software to find networking thing,
네, 네트워킹을 찾을 수 있는 소프트웨어를 제공하세요,
it wouldn't work because Kubernetes would be integrating
쿠버네티스가 통합할 것이기 때문에 작동하지 않을 것이다.
with 50,000 different things.
을 50,000개의 다른 것들과 통합할 것이기 때문이다.
And so the CNI is a standard that makes it possible
그래서 CNI는 이를 가능하게 하는 표준입니다.
for Kubernetes to make the requests that it wants to make,
쿠버네티스가 원하는 요청을 할 수 있도록 하는 표준이다,
like, hey, I've started up a pod
예를 들어, 내가 파드를 시작했어.
and I created a network namespace for it,
그리고 이를 위한 네트워크 네임스페이스를 생성했다,
but it's plain vanilla.
하지만 평범한 바닐라입니다.
There's no interfaces, there's no rules,
인터페이스도 없고, 규칙도 없어요,
there's no routes, there's nothing in there.
경로도 없고, 아무것도 없어요.
So hey, Mr. Software-Defined Networking thing,
이봐요, 소프트웨어 정의 네트워킹 씨,
please wire this pod up so that it can talk
이 포드가 대화할 수 있도록 연결해 주세요.
to other pods on this computer
이 컴퓨터의 다른 파드에
and any pod in the entire cluster.
그리고 전체 클러스터의 모든 파드에.
So the CNI solutions generally have at least one
따라서 CNI 솔루션은 일반적으로 적어도 하나 이상의
and sometimes two components.
그리고 때로는 두 개의 구성 요소가 있습니다.
The first component is a DaemonSet pod
첫 번째 컴포넌트는 데몬셋 파드이다.
that runs on every node in the cluster
클러스터의 모든 노드에서 실행된다.
and handles the organization of all the pods
모든 파드의 구성을 처리한다.
on that cluster.
해당 클러스터에서.
And then sometimes there's a control plane too.
그리고 때때로 컨트롤 플레인도 있습니다.
But those CNI components make it possible for pods
하지만 이러한 CNI 컴포넌트는 파드가
to reach each other when they're on different hosts.
이 서로 다른 호스트에 있을 때 서로 연결할 수 있다.
And they can do that in lots of different ways.
그리고 다양한 방법으로 이를 수행할 수 있습니다.
They can just use routes, right?
그냥 경로를 이용하면 되죠?
You can give every host a subnet,
모든 호스트에 서브넷을 부여할 수 있습니다,
and then the plugins can discover each other's subnets
그러면 플러그인이 서로의 서브넷을 발견할 수 있습니다.
through lots of ways, gossip, or they could use that CD
여러 가지 방법을 통해, 가십을 통해, 또는 그 CD를 사용할 수 있습니다.
to save all that information.
모든 정보를 저장할 수 있습니다.
And then once they get an outbound connection,
그리고 아웃바운드 연결을 받으면,
they can say, oh yeah, that IP address I know
내가 아는 IP 주소라고 말할 수 있습니다.
is on that host, so I'll just route the traffic.
이 해당 호스트에 있으므로 트래픽을 라우팅하면 됩니다.
They don't have to encapsulate it or do anything like that.
캡슐화하거나 그런 작업을 할 필요가 없습니다.
On the other hand, it's nice sometimes
반면에, 가끔은 좋죠.
to encapsulate the traffic because if you do,
를 사용하여 트래픽을 캡슐화할 수 있습니다,
then you can do things like encrypt it on the wire,
이면 유선에서 암호화하는 등의 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다,
you can do things like make sure that the underlying network
기본 네트워크에서 암호화하는 등의 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다.
doesn't know that there are pods, right?
파드가 있다는 것을 알지 못하죠?
It just sees two hosts talking to each other
두 호스트가 서로 대화하는 것만 본다.
instead of a bunch of, 20 different IP addresses
20개의 서로 다른 IP 주소가 아니라
from one computer.
한 컴퓨터에서.
If you try that on a cloud provider,
클라우드 제공업체에서 시도하는 경우,
they're probably gonna kill your traffic.
아마 트래픽을 죽일 것입니다.
They're gonna go, hey, that machine,
저기, 저 기계 말이야,
I know its IP address is .7,
IP 주소가 .7인 거 알아,
and I see all these crazy source IPs coming out of that box.
그리고 그 상자에서 나오는 모든 미친 소스 IP가 보입니다.
There's an attacker in there trying to spoof, right?
공격자가 스푸핑을 시도하고 있는 거죠?
And so of course you have to go to the cloud provider
그러니 당연히 클라우드 제공업체로 가서
and change settings to make all this stuff work.
이 모든 것이 작동하도록 설정을 변경해야 합니다.
If you just don't wanna have to worry about that,
그런 걱정을 하고 싶지 않으시다면요,
you want something that's totally portable
완전히 휴대 가능한 것을 원한다면
and goes from your bare metal environment to your cloud
베어메탈 환경에서 클라우드로 이동하는 경우
to somewhere else, then an overlay could be better, right?
다른 곳으로 이동한다면 오버레이가 더 낫겠죠?
So there's pros and cons to everything.
모든 일에는 장단점이 있는 법이죠.
There's no one right answer.
정답은 하나도 없어요.
But in the case of a lot of these plugins, you have choice.
하지만 많은 플러그인의 경우 선택의 여지가 있습니다.
So we're gonna talk about Cilium for just a second.
그럼 실리움에 대해 잠깐 이야기해보겠습니다.
We're gonna use it in the first lab.
첫 번째 실험실에서 사용할 거야.
Cilium is a CNI plugin that gives us options.
실리움은 우리에게 옵션을 제공하는 CNI 플러그인입니다.
And it is kind of in the new generation of CNIs
그리고 그것은 새로운 세대의 CNI에 속합니다.
that are trying to leverage eBPF.
eBPF를 활용하려고 합니다.
So there's a way to tell the Linux kernel
리눅스 커널에 다음과 같이 알릴 수 있는 방법이 있습니다.
to run little programs, and therefore it's very fast
작은 프로그램을 실행할 수 있으므로 매우 빠릅니다.
because you don't have a user mode component
사용자 모드 컴포넌트가 없기 때문입니다.
constantly messing around with the network traffic.
네트워크 트래픽을 계속 엉망으로 만들고 있습니다.
And so that's exactly how Cilium works.
이것이 바로 실리움이 작동하는 방식입니다.
It uses eBPF, leverages that,
실리움은 eBPF를 사용하고, 이를 활용합니다,
and Cilium gives you the ability to use an overlay network.
그리고 실리움은 오버레이 네트워크를 사용할 수 있는 기능을 제공합니다.
So you can tunnel the traffic between the hosts
따라서 호스트 간 트래픽을 터널링할 수 있습니다.
where the network underneath doesn't see the pod traffic.
아래 네트워크는 파드 트래픽을 볼 수 없다.
It just sees hosts talking.
호스트가 말하는 것만 본다.
Or you can route the traffic.
또는 트래픽을 라우팅할 수 있습니다.
It's up to you.
당신에게 달렸습니다.
Cilium gives you some flexibility
실리움은 유연성을 제공합니다
and it is a really cool CNCF project
정말 멋진 CNCF 프로젝트입니다
with a bunch of neat features.
깔끔한 기능들이 많아요.
So we're gonna use that as our CNI plugin,
그래서 우리는 그것을 CNI 플러그인으로 사용할 것입니다,
and that's gonna give us this.
그러면 이렇게 됩니다.
Now, you all have one node, right?
이제 모두 노드가 하나씩 있죠?
We already have like 400 computers stood up,
이미 400대의 컴퓨터가 일어섰어요,
so it would have been 800,
그래서 800대였을 겁니다,
and it just keeps going from there.
그리고 거기서부터 계속 진행됩니다.
So we're gonna do everything
그래서 우리는 모든 것을 할 거야
on a single node Kubernetes cluster,
단일 노드 쿠버네티스 클러스터에서,
but it's gonna work exactly the same
하지만 정확히 동일하게 작동한다.
as if you had 100 nodes, and that's the important thing,
마치 100개의 노드가 있는 것처럼, 그게 중요한 거죠,
and that's what Kubernetes and CNI
이것이 바로 쿠버네티스와 CNI의
brings to the table anyway.
의 차이점이다.
So if you had two hosts, for example,
예를 들어 호스트가 두 개라고 가정해봅시다,
the hosts have interfaces and the pods have interfaces,
호스트에는 인터페이스가 있고 파드에는 인터페이스가 있다,
and the CNI is the thing that takes care
그리고 CNI는 관리한다.
of making sure the traffic can get back and forth.
트래픽이 오갈 수 있도록 하는 것입니다.
All right, cool.
알았어요.
So we've sort of disambiguated CNI.
이제 CNI를 어느 정도 정리했네요.
We've talked about some of the solutions.
우리는 몇 가지 해결책에 대해 이야기했습니다.
There's lots of other really cool CNI plugins, by the way.
그나저나 정말 멋진 CNI 플러그인이 많이 있습니다.
Weave is another one that we use a lot at RXM
Weave는 RXM에서 많이 사용하는 또 다른 플러그인입니다.
because it's just super easy to install.
설치가 매우 쉽기 때문입니다.
Calico is probably one of the most popular ones out there
Calico는 아마도 가장 인기있는 것 중 하나 일 것입니다.
that a lot of people use as well, and the list goes on.
많은 사람들이 사용하고 있으며 목록은 계속됩니다.
So there's many, many options,
선택지가 정말 많습니다,
and they all have different pros and cons.
모두 다른 장단점을 가지고 있습니다.
But what we're gonna do now
하지만 이제 우리가 할 일은
is we are going to switch to lab mode,
실험실 모드로 전환하겠습니다,
and that link I put in the presentation, again, up here.
그리고 제가 프레젠테이션에 넣은 링크는 여기 위에 있습니다.
So you have it on your sheet.
이제 시트에 있습니다.
You also have it up there, right?
당신도 그 위에 있죠?
And there's a backup link too,
백업 링크도 있어요,
if you, for some reason, can't get to GitHub.
어떤 이유로든 깃허브에 접속할 수 없는 경우.
The reason we did the backup link
백업 링크를 만든 이유
is GitHub got flaky for me this morning.
오늘 아침에 깃허브에 문제가 생겼기 때문입니다.
I was like, whoa, somebody attacking GitHub?
누가 깃허브를 공격하는 거야?
That would be terrible.
끔찍하겠네.
And so we put a backup link.
그래서 백업 링크를 넣었습니다.
But I would just use the GitHub link
하지만 저는 그냥 GitHub 링크를 사용합니다.
because if you do, you're gonna get a nice,
그렇게 하면 멋진 걸 얻을 수 있으니까,
formatted webpage that you can just follow
형식의 웹페이지를 얻을 수 있으니까요.
and copy and paste from.
에서 복사하여 붙여넣을 수 있습니다.
Now, one thing I wanna mention is in the instructions,
이제 한 가지 언급하고 싶은 것은 지침에 있습니다,
it's walking you through all the steps.
모든 단계를 안내하고 있습니다.
So it says, hey, do this.
이걸 하라고 하네요.
And then it says, hey, do this.
그리고 이렇게 말하네요.
But some of these things say, hey, do this.
하지만 이런 것들 중 일부는 이렇게 말하죠.
And it's specific to your computer.
그리고 그것은 당신의 컴퓨터에만 해당됩니다.
For example, if you create a pod through a deployment,
예를 들어, 디플로이먼트를 통해 파드를 생성하는 경우,
that pod is gonna have an IP address
해당 파드는 IP 주소
that is unique to your setup.
설정에 고유한 IP 주소를 갖게 된다.
And another example here, pinging an IP.
또 다른 예는 IP를 핑하는 경우입니다.
Anytime you see an IP, you gotta ask yourself the question,
IP를 볼 때마다 스스로에게 질문을 던져야 합니다,
what IP should I be putting in there?
어떤 IP를 넣어야 할까?
Because it's not the one in the sheet.
시트에 있는 것이 아니니까요.
The lab is an example, and then you're gonna have
실험실은 예시일 뿐이고, 그 다음에는 다음과 같습니다.
to make some interpolations.
를 사용하여 보간을 합니다.
Usually it'll tell you.
보통은 이렇게 알려줍니다.
It says right here, note, there are lots
바로 여기에 이렇게 표시됩니다.
of different machines, use your IP address,
다른 컴퓨터의 IP 주소를 사용하세요,
that sort of thing.
그런 식으로요.
All right, so yeah, so that's lab step one.
좋아요, 이게 실험실 1단계입니다.
It's gonna have you, let me just kind of walk
널 잡을 거야, 그냥 걸어갈게.
through it real quick.
빨리 지나갈게요.
You can start right now if you want.
원하시면 지금 시작하셔도 됩니다.
So open this document up.
그럼 이 문서를 열어보세요.
You can read this little top section,
이 작은 상단 섹션을 읽을 수 있습니다,
and then it walks you through SSHing into the lab system.
그리고 나서 SSH를 통해 실험실 시스템에 접속하는 방법을 안내합니다.
It literally explains how to log in to the lab system
말 그대로 랩 시스템에 로그인하는 방법을 설명합니다.
with SSH if you've never done that before.
한 번도 해본 적이 없다면 SSH로 로그인하는 방법을 설명합니다.
Here's the link that I was mentioning
제가 언급했던 링크는 다음과 같습니다.
that can give you SSH help if you need that.
필요한 경우 SSH 도움말을 받을 수 있습니다.
And here's the link that shows you how to stand up
다음은 일어서는 방법을 알려주는 링크입니다.
one of these Ubuntu boxes on your own laptop
노트북에 이 우분투 박스 중 하나를 설치하세요.
so you can run the labs later if you wanna do that.
나중에 원하면 실험을 할 수 있게요.
So once you've done this, it has you install Kubernetes.
이 작업을 완료하면 쿠버네티스를 설치하게 됩니다.
We built a really cool little script
정말 멋진 작은 스크립트를 만들었습니다.
that does everything except set up the CNI plugin.
CNI 플러그인 설정을 제외한 모든 작업을 수행합니다.
So we're just gonna run that.
그럼 그냥 실행하겠습니다.
That's gonna take a minute or two,
1, 2분 정도 걸릴 거야,
so start that now if you can.
가능하면 지금 시작하세요.
And then you're gonna see the status of your nodes.
그러면 노드 상태를 확인할 수 있습니다.
You're gonna realize you need a CNI plugin.
CNI 플러그인이 필요하다는 것을 알게 될 것입니다.
We're gonna add Cilium.
실리움을 추가하겠습니다.
We're gonna play around with it a little bit.
이걸로 좀 놀아보자.
Then we're gonna poke around under the covers
그리고 이불 속을 뒤져볼게요.
and see how our pods work
우리 포드가 어떻게 작동하는지 보죠.
and how the IP addresses are getting assigned
IP 주소가 어떻게 할당되는지 확인한다.
and really just look at the whole IP space,
전체 IP 공간을 살펴볼 수 있습니다,
and then we'll clean up at the end.
그리고 마지막에 정리하겠습니다.
And so step two is services.
두 번째 단계는 서비스입니다.
I will indeed be breaking again for services
정말 서비스를 위해 다시 휴식을 취하겠습니다.
in a little bit, but if you get to the end of this lab
조금 있다가 이 실험이 끝나면
and we're not back into the discussion, keep going.
다시 논의하지 말고 계속 진행하세요.
Drill into the services.
서비스에 대해 자세히 알아보세요.
It's okay to get ahead because I'm pretty sure
앞서 나가도 괜찮아요.
you're gonna be behind at some point in this session.
이 세션의 어느 시점에서는 뒤처질 테니까요.
So yeah, SSH into your lab instance, install Kubernetes,
네, 랩 인스턴스에 SSH로 접속해서 쿠버네티스를 설치하세요,
set up CNI, and then explore the pod network.
CNI를 설정한 다음, 파드 네트워크를 탐색한다.
Have fun, holler if you have questions,
재미있게 사용하시고, 궁금한 점이 있으면 소리쳐주세요,
and I am, for the people who are virtual
그리고 나는, 가상의 사람들을 위해
and who don't have laptops,
노트북이 없는 사람들을 위해,
I'm gonna probably do these steps real quickly
이 단계는 정말 빨리 끝내야 할 것 같습니다.
on the overhead so you can just see them.
그냥 볼 수 있게 머리 위에 띄울게요.
All right, let me look at the time too.
좋아요, 시간도 볼게요.
Okay, what are we talking about here?
좋아, 이게 무슨 소리야?
So it is 11.23.
그래서 11.23입니다.
So this one might take a little bit of time.
시간이 좀 걸릴 수 있습니다.
I'm gonna give everybody till, say, 11.30,
모두에게 11시 30분까지 시간을 줄게요,
and then we'll do a check-in.
그리고 나서 체크인을 할게요.
All right.
알았어요.
Okay.
알았어.
All right.
알았어요.
Obviously you can use any SSH client you like.
물론 원하는 SSH 클라이언트를 사용할 수 있습니다.
I'm using Mobac's term, which I love,
제가 좋아하는 모박의 용어를 사용하고 있습니다,
and if you wanna use PuTTY, there's a PPK up there as well
PuTTY를 사용하고 싶으면 저기 PPK도 있어요.
in the keys, and I think it's on the sheet if you need it.
키에 있고, 필요하면 시트에 있을 거예요.
Okay.
알았어.
Hey, Valentin.
안녕, 발렌틴.
How many do we have left?
얼마나 남았어?
Do we have a lot left?
많이 남았나요?
Yeah.
그래.
Oh, cool, all right.
좋아, 알았어.
All right.
알았어.
All right, I just started the Kubernetes install on my,
좋아, 방금 쿠버네티스 설치를 시작했다,
well, I just grabbed a sheet just like you guys,
나도 방금 너희들처럼 시트를 가져왔어,
so I'm SSHed in.
SSH로 접속했어.
I'm running the Kubernetes install.
쿠버네티스 설치를 실행 중입니다.
It's installing Docker first.
도커를 먼저 설치하고 있습니다.
We're using Docker.
도커를 사용하고 있습니다.
That's the runtime.
런타임입니다.
Why Docker?
왜 도커일까요?
Docker's a poor choice for production,
도커는 프로덕션에 적합하지 않습니다,
not because Docker isn't amazing.
도커가 훌륭하지 않아서가 아닙니다.
Docker is amazing.
도커는 놀라워요.
It's just giant, and it has all sorts of stuff in it
그냥 거대하고, 모든 종류의 물건이 들어있어요.
that you don't want in your production environment.
프로덕션 환경에서는 원하지 않는 것들이죠.
If you're a developer or if you're experimenting,
개발자이거나 실험 중인 경우,
you want Docker, because it's awesome.
도커가 멋지니까요.
It has all sorts of cool tools and features and techniques
모든 종류의 멋진 도구와 기능, 기술이 있습니다.
that you can use for debugging and experimenting
디버깅과 실험에 사용할 수 있습니다.
and exploring, so that's why we use Docker here.
탐색을 위해 Docker를 사용하는 이유입니다.
We just install Docker, and then we install the Docker shim,
도커를 설치한 다음 도커 심을 설치합니다,
which no longer comes with Kubernetes,
더 이상 쿠버네티스와 함께 제공되지 않는다,
so you have to do both steps.
따라서 두 단계를 모두 수행해야 한다.
Docker's getting installed,
도커가 설치 중입니다,
then the Docker shim's getting installed,
도커 심이 설치되고 있습니다,
then we're gonna install Kubernetes latest, which is 1.23.
그러면 쿠버네티스 최신 버전인 1.23을 설치합니다.
You might also ask, what distribution of Kubernetes
쿠버네티스의 어떤 배포판인지 물어볼 수도 있다.
are we using, and the answer is none.
를 사용하고 있는지 물어볼 수 있는데, 대답은 '없음'이다.
We're just using upstream Kubernetes.
우리는 그냥 업스트림 쿠버네티스를 사용하고 있다.
Plain vanilla, 100%, completely compatible, the Kubernetes,
플레인 바닐라, 100%, 완벽하게 호환되는 쿠버네티스,
and we're using kubeadm to install it,
그리고 kubeadm을 사용하여 설치하고 있습니다,
which is the reference installer.
를 참조 인스톨러로 사용한다.
It's the node installer that runs underneath like kubespray
kubespray와 같이 아래에서 실행되는 노드 인스톨러이다.
and stuff like that, so no special gimmicks
같은 것들, 그래서 특별한 기믹은 없다.
in our clusters, just the basics,
우리 클러스터에서는 그냥 기본적인 것들입니다,
and the stuff we add, which is gonna be a lot.
그리고 우리가 추가하는 것들, 엄청나게 많을 겁니다.
Running this script is the thing that takes the longest,
이 스크립트를 실행하는 것이 가장 오래 걸리는 작업입니다,
so everything else is a lot shorter after this,
그 이후에는 다른 모든 것이 훨씬 짧아집니다,
and if you think about it, you're installing
그리고 생각해 보면, 여러분은
an entire Kubernetes cluster from nothing,
전체 쿠버네티스 클러스터를 무에서 유를 창조하는 것이다,
so that's not bad, just a minute or two there.
1, 2분 정도면 나쁘지 않습니다.
Just look at my node, it's not ready.
내 노드 좀 봐, 아직 준비 안 됐어.
It's not ready, because I don't have a CNI solution,
CNI 솔루션이 없어서 준비되지 않았습니다,
so I'm gonna read on in the lab.
실험실에서 계속 읽어볼게요.
Lab tells me your node's not ready.
실험실에서 노드가 준비되지 않았다고 합니다.
Now we're gonna install psyllium.
이제 실리움을 설치하겠습니다.
This is gonna make our node ready,
이제 노드가 준비됩니다,
and there's three steps here, which is, you know,
여기에는 세 단계가 있습니다,
I like to do everything kind of old school,
전 모든 걸 옛날 방식으로 하는 걸 좋아해요,
so you can see what's happening.
무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지 볼 수 있어요.
We're downloading a tarball, right?
타르볼을 다운로드하고 있죠?
That's the first piece, and then once we've got
그게 첫 번째 조각이고, 그 다음에는
the tarball downloaded, we have to extract it,
다운로드한 타르볼을 추출해야 합니다,
and that's gonna give us the psyllium CLI,
그러면 실리움 CLI를 얻을 수 있습니다,
so a lot of these kind of modern projects for Kubernetes
따라서 쿠버네티스를 위한 이러한 종류의 최신 프로젝트의 대부분은
use the operator pattern, where they actually have
연산자 패턴을 사용하는데, 실제로는
maybe a command line tool, and then they run a service
명령줄 도구를 사용하여 서비스를 실행합니다.
in Kubernetes that you can interact with,
쿠버네티스에서 상호 작용할 수 있다,
which is nice, because you can get data and things from it,
데이터와 물건을 가져올 수 있기 때문에 좋습니다,
and then that service is responsible for actually deploying
그리고 그 서비스가 실제로 배포를 담당한다.
the pods that are doing the thing you're trying to do,
하고자 하는 작업을 수행하는 파드를 배포한다,
so I have the psyllium CLI installed now.
그래서 이제 실리움 CLI를 설치했다.
I got my version information, but there's no psyllium
버전 정보를 얻었지만 실리움이 없습니다.
on my cluster.
내 클러스터에.
If I go back and do a get node, you know,
다시 돌아가서 get 노드를 수행하면,
still not ready, so I have to tell psyllium
아직 준비가 안됐으니 실리움에게 말해야겠어.
to install the CNI plugin, and that's the last step here
에 CNI 플러그인을 설치하라고 알려줘야 하고, 이것이 마지막 단계입니다.
before we are up and running.
실행하기 전에.
These guys, of course, have all sorts of crazy icons
물론 이 친구들은 온갖 종류의 미친 아이콘을 가지고 있습니다.
in their output, which is cute.
귀여운 아이콘을 가지고 있습니다.
And of course, every time you do one of these things,
그리고 물론, 이런 일을 할 때마다,
containers are being downloaded, right,
컨테이너가 다운로드되고 있습니다,
because everything runs in containers.
모든 것이 컨테이너에서 실행되기 때문입니다.
Kubernetes eats its own dog food.
쿠버네티스는 자신의 개밥을 먹는다.
Insofar as it's possible, when kube-adm installs things,
가능한 한, kube-adm이 무언가를 설치할 때,
anyway, the control plane runs in containers, in pods,
어쨌든, 컨트롤 플레인은 컨테이너, 파드에서 실행된다,
so you have the scheduler in a pod,
그래서 스케줄러가 파드에 있다,
you have the controller manager in a pod,
컨트롤러 매니저가 파드에 있다,
you have the kube-proxy in a prod,
프로드에 큐브-프록시가 있다,
the node agent, the kubelet, can't run in a pod
노드 에이전트인 kubelet이 파드에서 실행될 수 없다.
because it's the thing that creates the pods,
왜냐하면 그것이 파드를 생성하기 때문이다,
but beyond that, everything's in a pod.
하지만 그 너머에는 모든 것이 포드 안에 있습니다.
So now that we've got psyllium up and running,
이제 차전자피가 실행되고 있습니다,
we can do some things like ask it status.
상태를 물어보는 등의 작업을 할 수 있습니다.
All right, this is the nice thing about having a CLI
CLI를 사용하면 좋은 점은 다음과 같습니다.
and a control plane.
그리고 제어 평면.
We get all sorts of pretty colors,
온갖 예쁜 색을 얻습니다,
and so it looks good, right?
보기 좋죠?
We have the operator running, and we have a single node,
오퍼레이터가 실행 중이고 노드가 하나 있습니다,
so we have a single psyllium agent running.
따라서 하나의 실리움 에이전트가 실행 중입니다.
If we were running, you know, 40 nodes
만약 우리가 40개의 노드를 실행 중이라면
because it's a daemon set,
데몬 세트이기 때문입니다,
it would run on every single node,
모든 단일 노드에서 실행됩니다,
and there'd be 40 of them.
그리고 그 중 40개가 있을 것입니다.
We only have one node,
노드가 하나뿐입니다,
so we only have one of the psyllium plugins.
따라서 우리는 실리움 플러그인 중 하나만 가지고 있습니다.
All right?
알겠지?
And then it just has you look around
그리고 주위를 둘러보게 합니다.
and explore the network a little bit.
그리고 네트워크를 조금 탐색합니다.
Make sure traffic is going back and forth.
트래픽이 오가는지 확인합니다.
Has us run a little pod and verify that we can get to it,
작은 파드를 실행하고 접속할 수 있는지 확인합니다,
and we'll do that real quick.
아주 빨리 할게요.
We'll use the kubectl run command,
kubectl 실행 명령을 사용한다,
which essentially creates a manifest behind the scenes
이는 기본적으로 백그라운드에서 매니페스트를 생성한다.
and applies it to the cluster.
클러스터에 적용합니다.
So this one's gonna create a pod called web
이것은 웹이라는 파드를 생성한다.
with the image HTTPD and defaults for everything else.
라는 파드를 생성하고 다른 모든 것은 기본값을 사용합니다.
And then we can take a look at this guy.
이제 이 친구를 살펴볼 수 있습니다.
Output wide, and kubectl get pod
와이드 출력, 그리고 kubectl이 파드를 가져온다.
is gonna show us the IP of the pod,
는 파드의 IP를 보여준다,
and that way we can test it.
그러면 테스트할 수 있습니다.
All right, Apache up and running.
좋아, 아파치를 실행한다.
Thank you.
고마워요.
As more exploration goes on,
더 많은 탐사가 진행 중입니다,
we get a chance to take a look at the psyllium config,
차전자피의 구성을 살펴볼 기회를 얻습니다,
and I'll just run a couple more of these commands.
그리고 이 명령어들을 몇 개 더 실행해 보겠습니다.
All right, so this is the pool of IP addresses
자, 다음은 IP 주소 풀입니다.
that's gonna be handed out to our pods.
우리 파드에 나눠줄 주소입니다.
The lab kind of walks you through the different pools.
실험실에서 여러 풀을 안내해 주네요.
Right, we have the internet,
그래, 인터넷이 있네,
where everything goes except some reserved address ranges.
일부 예약된 주소 범위를 제외한 모든 것이 이동합니다.
Then you have your cloud host machines,
그러면 클라우드 호스트 머신이 있습니다,
which are probably using one of those reserved ranges.
이 예약된 범위 중 하나를 사용하고 있을 것입니다.
And then you have the pod network,
그리고 파드 네트워크가 있습니다,
which is inside that cloud.
이 클라우드 안에 있다.
And so these things all need to not conflict, right?
그래서 이 모든 것들이 충돌하지 않아야 하죠?
You don't wanna conflict with the public IP address
공인 IP 주소와 충돌하고 싶지 않으시겠죠?
because they might need to reach you or vice versa.
상대방이 나에게 연락해야 할 수도 있고 그 반대일 수도 있기 때문입니다.
You could proxy them,
프록시할 수 있습니다,
but and you don't wanna conflict with the host IPs.
하지만 호스트 IP와 충돌하고 싶지 않을 것입니다.
That would be confusing.
혼란스러울 수 있습니다.
And then the pod IP space is also gonna need to be unique.
그리고 파드 IP 공간도 고유해야 한다.
When you set up your cluster,
클러스터를 설정할 때,
you can specify the IP range for services,
서비스에 대한 IP 범위를 지정할 수 있습니다,
as we'll see in a minute,
잠시 후에 살펴보겠습니다,
but it's the CNI that decides what IP address your pod gets.
하지만 파드가 어떤 IP 주소를 갖게 될지는 CNI가 결정한다.
That's why it's set up here in the CNI function.
이것이 바로 여기 CNI 함수에서 설정하는 이유이다.
So if you wanted a different range,
다른 범위를 원한다면
you'd have to tell psyllium when you installed it.
설치했을 때 실리움에게 알려줘야 합니다.
And if you do a psyllium install minus minus help,
그리고 실리움 설치 마이너스 마이너스 도움말을 수행하면,
it'll dump out a gazillion options that you can use.
사용할 수 있는 수많은 옵션을 덤프합니다.
And there's also a config that you can set and apply
그리고 설정하고 적용할 수 있는 구성도 있습니다.
in kind of a more infrastructure as code approach.
을 설정하여 적용할 수 있습니다.
All right, and so we test the pod network out,
자, 이제 파드 네트워크를 테스트합니다,
do a couple more things.
몇 가지 작업을 더 한다.
And then finally we clean up at the end.
그리고 마지막에 청소를 합니다.
Didn't actually create the client,
실제로 클라이언트를 생성하지 않았습니다,
but I'm gonna go ahead and just delete the web guy
그냥 웹 녀석을 삭제할게요.
and call it a day here.
여기까지 하겠습니다.
Step one done for me.
1단계는 끝났습니다.
You just do a quick show of hands.
손만 빨리 내밀면 됩니다.
If you're still working, great.
아직 일하고 있다면 다행이네요.
How many people have finished with step one though?
1단계를 완료한 사람은 몇 명인가요?
Okay, great.
좋아요.
Let's move on.
계속 진행하죠.
If you're still working, that's great.
아직 일하고 있다면 다행이네요.
Don't feel slow.
느리다고 느끼지 마세요.
You're probably going really fast actually,
실제로는 정말 빨리 가고 있을 거예요,
but we're gonna try to keep on the clock here.
하지만 여기서 계속 시간을 맞추도록 노력할게요.
So give me half an ear while you're keep working
그러니 계속 작업하는 동안 내 귀를 반쯤 열어줘.
if you want to.
원한다면.
This is a tutorial.
튜토리얼입니다.
It's all about the hands-on.
실습에 관한 모든 것.
So if you have a choice between ignoring me
날 무시할지, 아니면
and doing the lab and not ignoring me, I would ignore me.
날 무시하고 실험을 하는 것과 날 무시하지 않고 실험을 하는 것 중 하나를 선택할 수 있다면 난 날 무시할 거야.
So Kubernetes Service Communications.
그래서 쿠버네티스 서비스 커뮤니케이션.
Let's take a look at how Kubernetes thinks about services.
쿠버네티스가 서비스에 대해 어떻게 생각하는지 살펴보자.
When you are running pods,
파드를 실행할 때,
let's think about Kubernetes 1.0.
쿠버네티스 1.0에 대해 생각해 보자.
Kubernetes 1.0 was for microservices, period.
쿠버네티스 1.0은 마이크로서비스를 위한 것이었다.
End of story.
이야기 끝.
There were no real provisions
실제 조항은 없었습니다.
for any kind of stateful workloads.
모든 종류의 스테이트풀 워크로드에 대해.
Cassandra is not a microservice, right?
카산드라는 마이크로서비스가 아니죠?
It is a clustered storage engine
클러스터형 스토리지 엔진입니다.
where you run many, many nodes
많은 노드를 실행하는 곳
and it's horizontally scalable
그리고 수평적으로 확장 가능합니다.
and it's absolutely a cloud-friendly kind of data store,
그리고 클라우드 친화적인 데이터 저장소입니다,
but it's not a microservice.
하지만 마이크로서비스는 아닙니다.
Microservices are stateless.
마이크로서비스는 상태가 없습니다.
State is hard.
상태가 어렵습니다.
Scaling your Cassandra cluster, sizing it,
카산드라 클러스터를 확장하고 크기를 조정하는 중입니다,
doing all those things is hard,
그 모든 일을 하는 것은 어렵습니다,
but running a microservice is easy
하지만 마이크로서비스를 실행하는 것은 쉽습니다.
and destroying it when you have seven others
다른 7개가 있을 때 파괴합니다.
shouldn't ripple the waters at all.
물결이 전혀 일어나지 않아야 합니다.
Nobody should care.
아무도 신경 쓸 필요 없어.
You get disconnected, you reconnect,
연결이 끊어졌다가 다시 연결됩니다,
and you end up with one of the other guys
그리고 다른 남자 중 한 명과 만나게 된다.
and they're all the same.
모두 똑같아.
That's what microservices are all about.
이것이 바로 마이크로서비스의 핵심입니다.
And so Kubernetes embraces this.
그래서 쿠버네티스는 이를 수용합니다.
And so we can run a whole bunch of copies of our service
그래서 우리는 우리 서비스의 전체 사본을 실행할 수 있습니다.
under a deployment in Kubernetes.
를 실행할 수 있습니다.
And then to avoid customers
그리고 고객을 피하기 위해
having to worry about the mayhem of pods scaling up and down
파드의 확장 및 축소로 인한 대혼란을 걱정해야 한다.
and getting deleted because a node is overloaded
노드에 과부하가 걸려서 삭제될 수 있다.
or whatever, we put a service in front of it.
또는 그 앞에 서비스를 넣습니다.
And that service has a head, a cluster IP,
그리고 그 서비스에는 헤드, 즉 클러스터 IP가 있습니다,
a virtual IP address.
가상 IP 주소가 있습니다.
It's not associated with any interface.
어떤 인터페이스와도 연결되어 있지 않습니다.
It's just an IP.
그냥 IP입니다.
And when you try to connect to it,
그리고 접속을 시도하면,
the Linux kernel has to figure out what to do
리눅스 커널은 무엇을 해야할지 알아내야 합니다.
because that address isn't associated with anything.
해당 주소는 아무 것도 연결되어 있지 않기 때문입니다.
There's nowhere to send the packets, right?
패킷을 보낼 곳이 없죠?
And so Kubernetes implements the routing functionality,
그래서 쿠버네티스는 라우팅 기능을 구현한다,
the forwarding functionality that makes that all work.
이 모든 것을 작동하게 하는 포워딩 기능을 구현한다.
When you create a service, you get a cluster IP
서비스를 생성하면 클러스터 IP를 얻습니다.
and you get the wiring that delivers your connection
그리고 연결을 제공하는 배선을 얻는다.
to one of those backend pods.
백엔드 파드 중 하나에 연결됩니다.
So how do we make that go?
어떻게 하면 될까요?
Well, there's a thing called the kube-proxy.
큐브 프록시라는 것이 있습니다.
It runs in a pod as a daemon set
이것은 파드에서 데몬 세트로 실행된다.
on every node in the cluster.
클러스터의 모든 노드에서 실행된다.
And it's doing that stuff.
그리고 그 일을 하고 있습니다.
Its job is every time a service is created,
서비스가 생성될 때마다 그 일을 합니다,
so it's watching the API server saying,
이므로 API 서버를 감시하고 있습니다,
hey, tell me about any services.
어떤 서비스가 있는지 알려주세요.
And when a service gets created,
그리고 서비스가 생성되면,
it immediately goes and tells the Linux kernel
즉시 리눅스 커널에 알린다.
do all this stuff, right?
이 모든 작업을 수행합니다.
And now all of a sudden,
그리고 이제 갑자기,
people can reach those pods through those services.
사람들이 해당 서비스를 통해 해당 파드에 도달할 수 있습니다.
And when pods come and go,
그리고 파드가 왔다 갔다 할 때,
the kube-proxy is watching that too.
큐브-프록시는 그것도 보고 있다.
If a pod goes away, he takes that pod out of the mesh.
파드가 사라지면, 그 파드를 메시에서 제거한다.
If a pod shows up and has the right label,
파드가 나타나고 올바른 레이블을 가진 경우,
he adds that pod into the mesh.
해당 파드를 메시에 추가한다.
So the kube-proxy is the magic.
큐브-프록시는 마법과도 같다.
Now, how does the kube-proxy make this work?
이제, kube-proxy는 어떻게 작동할까요?
Well, the slowest way is it can do user mode.
가장 느린 방법은 사용자 모드를 사용하는 것이다.
But this is deprecated and, you know,
하지만 이것은 더 이상 사용되지 않습니다,
this was used in the early beta days of Kubernetes
이것은 쿠버네티스 초기 베타 시절에 사용되었다.
where the traffic would literally connect to the proxy
트래픽이 말 그대로 프록시에 연결되는 위치.
and then the proxy would make the connection
그리고 나서 프록시가 연결합니다.
outbound for you.
아웃바운드합니다.
So that's no good because now you've got a user mode process
이제 사용자 모드 프로세스가 있으므로 좋지 않습니다.
and your data path's gonna be slow.
데이터 경로가 느려질 테니까요.
So the next thing we can do is use IP tables.
다음으로 할 수 있는 일은 IP 테이블을 사용하는 것입니다.
We just tell the kernel, hey,
커널에 이렇게 말하면 됩니다,
when somebody connects to this IP address,
라고 알려주면 됩니다,
use a destination network address translation
대상 네트워크 주소 변환 사용
to one of these pods.
이 파드 중 하나로.
A lot of people don't know it,
많은 사람들이 모릅니다,
but you can randomly select a rule in a chain of rules
하지만 규칙 체인에서 규칙을 임의로 선택할 수 있습니다.
in IP tables and that's what's happening, right?
를 선택할 수 있습니다.
So if there's 20 services back there,
뒤에 20개의 서비스가 있다면,
it's just gonna randomly select one of them
그 중 하나를 무작위로 선택합니다.
and then send you to that guy.
그 남자에게 널 보낼 거야
So it's load balancing, right?
로드 밸런싱이 되는 거죠?
It's random, but it's load balancing.
무작위이긴 하지만 로드 밸런싱을 하는 거죠.
And if pods are coming and going like crazy
그리고 파드가 미친 듯이 왔다 갔다 한다면
and one of the pods gets overloaded,
그리고 파드 중 하나에 과부하가 걸린다,
that pod's likely to be evicted
해당 파드가 퇴거될 가능성이 있다.
and all those connections are gonna break
모든 연결이 끊어질 거야
and they're gonna redistribute immediately
즉시 재분배됩니다.
because the clients are gonna reconnect.
클라이언트가 다시 연결할 것이기 때문입니다.
If you're talking to a microservice,
마이크로서비스와 대화하는 경우,
you should expect it to be ephemeral, right?
일시적일 거라고 예상해야 하죠?
Note to people writing client code,
클라이언트 코드를 작성하는 사람들에게 참고하세요,
expect that connection to break.
연결이 끊어질 것을 예상하세요.
Don't be surprised by it.
놀라지 마세요.
When it does, you just reconnect
다시 연결하면 됩니다.
and you're gonna get distributed to somebody else.
다른 사람에게 배포됩니다.
So the entropy of the cluster naturally distributes the load
따라서 클러스터의 엔트로피는 자연스럽게 부하를 분산시킵니다.
pretty darn well.
꽤나 잘 됩니다.
A lot of people are like,
많은 사람들이 좋아합니다,
let's use some sophisticated global rate limit,
좀 더 정교한 글로벌 속도 제한을 사용해 봅시다,
blah, blah, blah.
어쩌고저쩌고.
And at the end of the day, try it.
그리고 하루가 끝나면 해보세요.
Try the simple stuff first.
간단한 것부터 해보세요.
It's often fastest, right?
그게 가장 빠를 때가 많죠?
But if that doesn't work for you, there's other options.
하지만 그래도 안 된다면 다른 방법이 있습니다.
Now, one thing that probably is an upgrade is IPVS.
업그레이드할 수 있는 한 가지 방법은 IPVS입니다.
So the kernel has also another mechanism,
커널에는 또 다른 메커니즘이 있습니다,
IP virtual services,
IP 가상 서비스,
and it's a little bit, a teeny bit faster than IP tables
IP 테이블보다 약간, 아주 약간 빠릅니다.
in some situations and a lot faster in some others
어떤 상황에서는 더 빠르고 어떤 상황에서는 훨씬 빠릅니다.
because it uses a lot less resources.
훨씬 적은 리소스를 사용하기 때문입니다.
That's the main thing.
그게 중요한 거죠.
IP tables were never meant to be distributing traffic.
IP 테이블은 트래픽을 분산시키려는 의도가 아니었습니다.
So IPVS is probably the better option.
따라서 IPVS가 더 나은 옵션일 것입니다.
You can tell kube-proxy which of these modes you wanna use,
이 모드 중 어떤 모드를 사용할지 kube-proxy에게 알려주면 된다,
and the default is IP tables.
기본값은 IP 테이블이다.
So that's the one that we're using in our lab
이것이 저희 연구실에서 사용하는 주소입니다.
because we didn't tell it to do anything else, right?
우리가 다른 걸 시키지 않았으니까요, 그렇죠?
There are also CNI plugins that have fancy features too
멋진 기능을 가진 CNI 플러그인도 있습니다.
because EVPF, hey, programming the kernel
왜냐하면 EVPF는 커널을 프로그래밍하기 때문이다.
sounds like that would be a way
그게 방법인 것 같네요
to handle these services too, right?
이런 서비스도 처리할 수 있겠죠?
Well, it is, and it has some benefits.
네, 그리고 몇 가지 장점이 있습니다.
So some of the plugins let you do that.
그래서 몇몇 플러그인은 그렇게 할 수 있게 해줍니다.
You could replace the kube-proxy with Cilium
큐브-프록시를 실리움으로 대체할 수 있다.
if you wanted to and let it do all that stuff.
로 대체할 수 있다.
We didn't tell it to do that again, so it didn't,
다시 하라고 하지 않았기 때문에 그렇게 하지 않았어요,
but that's an option that's on the table.
하지만 그것은 테이블 위에 있는 옵션입니다.
Now remember that all of the hosts
이제 모든 호스트가
in your cloud, virtual private cloud, right,
클라우드, 가상 사설 클라우드에 있습니다,
have to have unique addresses
고유한 주소가 있어야 합니다.
if they're gonna talk to each other.
서로 대화하려면 말이죠.
So all your Kubernetes cluster nodes
따라서 모든 쿠버네티스 클러스터 노드는
have to have unique addresses.
는 고유한 주소를 가져야 한다.
And then all of the pods that run in them
그리고 그 안에서 실행되는 모든 파드들은
have to have unique addresses.
고유한 주소를 가져야 한다.
And since you need to be able to get to the pods
그리고 파드에 도달할 수 있어야 하므로
from the host in order to do things
작업을 수행하려면 호스트에서
like check their health and stuff,
건강 체크 같은 거요,
those addresses have to be unique, right, non-overlapping.
이 주소들은 고유하고, 맞고, 겹치지 않아야 합니다.
And then the last thing is the service IPs
그리고 마지막은 서비스 IP입니다.
need to be unique and non-overlapping.
는 고유하고 겹치지 않아야 합니다.
So we have three address spaces we gotta think about
따라서 고려해야 할 세 가지 주소 공간이 있습니다.
when we're setting up Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스를 설정할 때.
This is part of the architecting a cluster process, right?
이것은 클러스터를 설계하는 과정의 일부죠?
What are the address ranges we're gonna use
사용할 주소 범위는 무엇인가요?
for these things?
이런 것들은?
And another interesting thing
그리고 또 다른 흥미로운 것
is the support for IPv4 and IPv6.
는 IPv4와 IPv6를 지원한다는 점입니다.
We're doing everything in IPv4 for no reason.
이유 없이 모든 것을 IPv4로 하고 있습니다.
It's just what happens by default, right?
원래 이렇게 되는 거잖아요?
This is the way things work by default.
이게 기본적으로 작동하는 방식입니다.
But out there on the internet,
하지만 인터넷에서는,
IPv6 continues to gain steam.
IPv6는 계속해서 힘을 얻고 있습니다.
A lot of companies, especially telcos,
많은 기업, 특히 통신사들,
are IPv6 internally everywhere.
내부적으로 모든 곳에서 IPv6를 사용합니다.
And so there's a good momentum towards IPv6.
따라서 IPv6를 향한 좋은 모멘텀이 있습니다.
In Kubernetes 1.0, it was IPv4.
쿠버네티스 1.0에서는 IPv4였다.
That was the end of the story.
이것이 이야기의 끝이었다.
Next, IPv6 only went GA in 1.18, right?
다음으로, IPv6는 1.18에서야 정식 버전으로 전환되었죠?
That was a long time later.
그건 한참 후의 일이었죠.
And you had one or the other, right?
둘 중 하나는 가지고 있었죠?
Not both.
둘 다 아니야.
You could pick one, right?
하나만 고르면 되죠?
And this is as far as what Kubernetes is responsible for.
쿠버네티스가 담당하는 것은 여기까지다.
So the cluster IPs, right?
클러스터 IP 맞죠?
If you had a CNI plugin that knew how to do IPv6,
IPv6를 수행하는 방법을 알고 있는 CNI 플러그인이 있다면,
well, knock yourself out.
뭐, 마음껏 해보세요.
That's fine.
괜찮아.
But the services are always gonna be IPv4 or IPv6
하지만 서비스는 항상 IPv4 또는 IPv6입니다.
until 1.20,
1.20까지
where we got either IPv4 or IPv6 in the same cluster, right?
같은 클러스터에서 IPv4 또는 IPv6를 사용하는 경우 맞죠?
Now you could pick.
이제 선택할 수 있습니다.
You could have an IPv4 service over here
여기에 IPv4 서비스가 있을 수 있습니다.
and an IPv6 over here.
그리고 여기는 IPv6.
Pretty cool.
꽤 멋지네요.
But you still couldn't have a dual stack service, right?
하지만 여전히 듀얼 스택 서비스를 할 수는 없죠?
That was out of bounds.
그건 한계를 벗어났어요.
Until, da-na, one, two, three.
다-나, 하나, 둘, 셋까지.
Three weeks ago or whatever it was,
3주 전인지 뭔지 모르겠지만,
we now have GA, IPv4, IPv6 dual stack.
이제 GA, IPv4, IPv6 듀얼 스택이 생겼습니다.
So you can pick on a cluster to make a service single stack.
이제 클러스터를 선택해서 서비스 싱글 스택을 만들 수 있습니다.
You can make it prefer dual stack.
듀얼 스택을 선호하도록 만들 수 있습니다.
And then you can require dual stack.
그리고 듀얼 스택을 요구할 수 있습니다.
And that means that the users got to have both, right?
사용자가 두 가지를 모두 가지고 있어야 한다는 뜻이죠?
So those are pretty cool features.
꽤 멋진 기능들이네요.
The Kubernetes project is really stunning,
쿠버네티스 프로젝트는 정말 놀랍습니다,
how fast it moves and how much tech is in it
얼마나 빠르게 움직이고 얼마나 많은 기술이 들어있는지
when you look at all the different places
모든 다른 장소를 볼 때
and how advanced it is.
그리고 그것이 얼마나 발전했는지.
So some things are a long time coming.
그래서 어떤 것들은 오래 걸립니다.
That maybe was, but hey, it's here now.
그랬을지도 모르지만 지금은 여기 있잖아.
Services, how do we create one?
서비스, 어떻게 만들 수 있나요?
Well, in Kubernetes, you pretty much create everything
쿠버네티스에서는 거의 모든 것을 생성할 수 있다.
by specifying it and giving the specification to Kubernetes.
지정하고 쿠버네티스에 사양을 제공함으로써.
And then Kubernetes just spends the rest of its life
그리고 쿠버네티스는 남은 수명을 보낸다.
trying to make the status of the cluster
클러스터의 상태를 확인하려고 한다.
the same as your specifications.
사양과 동일하게 만들려고 합니다.
That's what Kubernetes does.
이것이 쿠버네티스가 하는 일이다.
It makes the status of the cluster
클러스터의 상태를 만든다.
the same as your specifications.
으로 변경합니다.
That way, you don't have to constantly get up
이렇게 하면 계속 일어날 필요가 없습니다.
in the middle of the night and say,
한밤중에 일어나서
oh, that pod stopped, let me restart it.
아, 그 포드가 멈췄어요. 다시 시작하겠습니다.
No, you said I want a pod running,
아니, 파드를 실행하라고 했잖아,
and if it stops, Kubernetes restarts it.
그리고 멈추면 쿠버네티스가 다시 시작한다.
Self-healing, all these types of automate the toil,
자가 치유, 이 모든 유형의 수고를 자동화합니다,
SRE stuff.
SRE 물건들.
So this is a service.
이것은 서비스입니다.
It's a very simple one.
아주 간단한 서비스입니다.
It has a name, web.
웹이라는 이름이 있습니다.
It has a port, 80.
포트가 80입니다.
The port has a name, too.
포트에 이름도 있습니다.
And in case you have multiple ports,
포트가 여러 개인 경우
you can use SRV records and DNS
SRV 레코드와 DNS를 사용할 수 있습니다.
to discover which ones are which and stuff.
를 사용하여 어떤 것이 어떤 것인지 알아낼 수 있습니다.
And then we have a selector that says,
그리고 다음과 같은 선택기가 있습니다,
hey, any pod that has the label key app value web
이봐, 레이블 키 앱 값 웹이 있는 모든 파드는
gets this traffic.
이 트래픽을 받는다.
So if there's 100 of them,
만약 100개라면
you'll have 100 of those pods getting connections
100개의 파드가 연결을 받게 된다.
when this service is hit.
이 서비스가 히트될 때.
If there's one of them, then that one will get it.
둘 중 하나가 있으면 그 하나가 가져갑니다.
If there's none, then you can't connect.
아무도 없으면 연결할 수 없습니다.
There's no such thing as a virtual IP.
가상 IP 같은 것은 없습니다.
It's a virtual.
가상이에요.
It's just rules in a table or something like that.
그냥 테이블에 있는 규칙 같은 거야.
So if there aren't any pods,
그래서 만약 파드가 없다면,
you're not gonna go any further.
더 이상 진행하지 않습니다.
So that's the idea behind a service.
이것이 바로 서비스의 개념입니다.
Now, all of the pods that match that selector
이제, 해당 셀렉터와 일치하는 모든 파드들은
create something called an endpoint.
엔드포인트라는 것을 생성한다.
The service could push all the pod information
서비스가 모든 파드 정보를 푸시할 수 있다.
that match the service down to all the queue proxies.
모든 큐 프록시로 푸시할 수 있다.
But that'd be very expensive
하지만 비용이 많이 듭니다.
because you can have clusters
클러스터를 가질 수 있기 때문입니다.
with thousands and thousands of pods.
수천, 수만 개의 파드를 가질 수 있기 때문입니다.
And so what's better is to just create a little thing
그래서 더 좋은 것은 그냥 작은 것을 만드는 것이다.
that has the IP address, and that's about it,
를 생성하는 것입니다,
an endpoint that identifies the targets that you want
원하는 대상을 식별하는 엔드포인트입니다.
and then you send those down to the queue proxy.
그런 다음 이를 큐 프록시로 보냅니다.
So earlier I said, hey, the queue proxy's watching the pods.
앞서 큐 프록시가 파드를 보고 있다고 말씀드렸습니다.
It's actually looking for endpoints, right?
실제로 엔드포인트를 찾고 있는 거죠?
And so the service controller is creating the endpoints
그래서 서비스 컨트롤러가 엔드포인트를 생성하고 있습니다.
and then the queue proxy is getting those.
그리고 큐 프록시가 이를 받습니다.
So an endpoint looks like this up here.
여기서 엔드포인트는 다음과 같이 보입니다.
What happens if you create a service that has no selector?
선택기가 없는 서비스를 만들면 어떻게 될까요?
That service will never ever identify any pods
이 서비스는 어떤 파드도 식별하지 못한다.
to send traffic to.
트래픽을 보낼 수 있다.
So you're gonna have to do it.
그러니 당신이 해야 합니다.
And this is something that you might do
그리고 이것은 당신이 할 수 있는 일입니다.
in a scenario where those pods aren't pods.
해당 파드가 파드가 아닌 시나리오에서.
What if you have 16 VMs?
VM이 16개라면?
And every once in a while, some of them shut down
그리고 가끔씩 그 중 일부가 종료됩니다.
and some new ones stand up.
그리고 새로운 것들이 일어납니다.
You could create your own glue to create these endpoints.
이러한 엔드포인트를 만들기 위해 자신만의 글루를 만들 수 있습니다.
And because the endpoint is named website,
그리고 엔드포인트의 이름이 웹사이트이기 때문에,
we know it's a sub-resource of the service website.
서비스 웹사이트의 하위 리소스임을 알 수 있습니다.
And then it's got an address and the ports,
그리고 주소와 포트가 있습니다,
just like we had before defined on the service side.
앞서 서비스 측에서 정의한 것과 같습니다.
And then next thing you know,
그리고 그 다음에는
you look at the endpoints for your service
서비스의 엔드포인트를 확인합니다.
and this guy shows up if you apply that endpoint.
해당 엔드포인트를 적용하면 이 녀석이 나타납니다.
So you can create your own endpoints.
따라서 여러분만의 엔드포인트를 만들 수 있습니다.
You can have them produced dynamically by Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스가 동적으로 생성하도록 할 수 있다.
So in general, if you're routing the pods,
따라서 일반적으로 파드를 라우팅하는 경우,
you would want them dynamically created.
동적으로 생성되기를 원할 것이다.
Now, what kinds of services do we have to work with?
이제 어떤 종류의 서비스와 함께 작업해야 할까요?
There's a bunch.
많아요.
The first kind is a headless service.
첫 번째 종류는 헤드리스 서비스입니다.
A headless service has no cluster IP.
헤드리스 서비스에는 클러스터 IP가 없습니다.
You literally say cluster IP none.
말 그대로 클러스터 IP가 없습니다.
It actually turns out it's a cluster IP type of service
실제로는 클러스터 IP 유형의 서비스인 것으로 밝혀졌습니다.
with no cluster IP.
클러스터 IP가 없습니다.
I don't know how that works, but anyway.
어떻게 작동하는지 모르겠지만 어쨌든.
You define a headless service by creating
헤드리스 서비스를 정의하려면
a cluster IP service with no cluster IP.
클러스터 IP가 없는 클러스터 IP 서비스.
What is that good for?
이게 무슨 의미일까요?
It's good for situations where the pods aren't the same.
포드가 동일하지 않은 상황에 유용합니다.
What if one of your pods is a Kafka pod
파드 중 하나가 카프카 파드라면?
and it has the topic NASDAQ?
토픽이 NASDAQ이고?
And what if the other of your pods is a Kafka pod
다른 파드가 카프카 파드라면 어떨까?
and it has on it the topic New York Stock Exchange?
뉴욕 증권 거래소라는 주제를 가지고 있다면?
And another pod has life and so on, right?
그리고 다른 포드에는 생명 등이 있죠?
Well, you can't connect to the life pod
생명체 포드에 연결할 수 없습니다.
if you want to get the New York Stock Exchange data.
뉴욕 증권 거래소 데이터를 얻고 싶다면.
They have identity, these pods.
이 포드들은 정체성이 있어요.
They're not microservices.
마이크로서비스가 아니다.
So anytime you have a situation
따라서 어떤 상황이 발생하면
where they're not microservices,
마이크로서비스가 아닌 경우,
but you want DNS resolution and stuff like that,
하지만 DNS 확인과 같은 것을 원합니다,
this is the kind of service you want.
이런 종류의 서비스를 원합니다.
Next, cluster IP.
다음은 클러스터 IP입니다.
Cluster IP is for microservices, right?
클러스터 IP는 마이크로서비스용이죠?
Where it just sends the traffic.
트래픽을 보내는 곳입니다.
That's the first example we looked at.
이것이 우리가 살펴본 첫 번째 예제입니다.
Node port is another one where if packets are coming in
노드 포트는 패킷이 들어올 경우
from the outside world
외부 세계로부터
and we want them to be delivered to our service,
우리 서비스로 전달되기를 원합니다,
we can use a port on every node,
모든 노드에서 포트를 사용할 수 있습니다,
on every host in the cluster
클러스터의 모든 호스트에서
and have that port forward to our service.
해당 포트를 우리 서비스로 전달합니다.
So that port is reserved for us in the entire cluster.
따라서 해당 포트는 전체 클러스터에서 우리를 위해 예약됩니다.
So obviously the control plane needs to know
따라서 당연히 컨트롤 플레인은 다음을 알아야 합니다.
what port range you want to use
어떤 포트 범위를 사용할지
and it needs to be in control
그리고 제어해야 합니다.
of which ports are handed out and so on.
어떤 포트가 분배되는지 등등.
So we'll look at node port a little bit more later.
노드 포트는 나중에 조금 더 살펴보겠습니다.
Load balancer is like node port,
로드밸런서는 노드 포트와 같습니다,
except it also stands up an external load balancer.
외부 로드밸런서를 세운다는 점만 다릅니다.
This requires a plugin, right?
이거 플러그인이 필요한 거죠?
We have to have some sort of external thing
뭔가 외부적인 것이 있어야 합니다.
like an Azure load balancer
Azure 로드 밸런서 같은 것
or a Google Cloud network load balancer
또는 구글 클라우드 네트워크 로드 밸런서
or something to interact with
또는 상호 작용할 무언가
or a Metal LB as we were looking at earlier.
또는 앞서 살펴본 메탈 LB입니다.
And then lastly, we have external name.
마지막으로 외부 이름이 있습니다.
This is for scenarios where you have a service name
이것은 서비스 이름이 있는 시나리오를 위한 것입니다.
that you want to be resolvable inside your cluster.
클러스터 내에서 확인할 수 있는 서비스 이름이 있는 경우입니다.
We're gonna look at DNS more in the next module,
다음 모듈에서 DNS에 대해 자세히 살펴보겠습니다,
but you actually want it to look for some name
하지만 실제로는 어떤 이름을 찾기를 원합니다.
that's outside your cluster, right?
클러스터 밖에 있는 거 맞죠?
So you're gonna make a name mapping
그래서 네임 매핑을 만들 거야.
and you can do that with external name.
외부 이름을 사용하면 됩니다.
All right, so lab step two.
자, 실험실 2단계입니다.
We're going to create a deployment,
배포를 생성하겠습니다,
which is gonna have several pods.
여러 개의 파드가 있을 것이다.
We're gonna create a cluster IP service.
클러스터 IP 서비스를 생성한다.
We're gonna connect to the service,
서비스에 연결하겠습니다,
see the traffic, reach the deployment and come back.
트래픽을 확인하고 배포에 도달한 후 다시 돌아옵니다.
And then we're gonna figure out how it works.
그리고 나서 어떻게 작동하는지 알아볼 겁니다.
We're gonna get under the covers, look at the IP tables,
이불 속으로 들어가서 IP 테이블을 살펴볼게요,
poke around a little bit and see how things are happening.
좀 더 들여다보고 상황을 살펴볼게요.
Okay, so we are looking at 1147.
자, 1147을 보고 있습니다.
1147, how is that possible?
1147, 이게 어떻게 가능하지?
Okay, let's give everybody say eight minutes.
자, 모두에게 8분을 주자.
We'll come back at 55 minutes after.
55분 후에 다시 오겠습니다.
Nothing to install in this session, so.
이 세션에는 설치할 것이 없습니다.
But there is a lot of stuff to look at.
하지만 볼 것이 많습니다.
So 1155 and we will be coming back.
1155, 다시 돌아올게요.
Okay, so I'm gonna go ahead and do this second step
자, 이제 두 번째 단계를 수행하겠습니다.
for people virtual, just so you can get an idea
가상의 사람들을 위해, 그냥 아이디어를 얻을 수 있도록.
of what's happening here and I'll talk through it.
여기서 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지 설명해줄게요.
But for the people locally, you can just ignore me
하지만 현지 사람들은 그냥 무시해도 돼요.
and work on the lab yourself.
직접 실험실에서 일해.
So first thing we're gonna do is we need some pods
가장 먼저 할 일은 포드 몇 개가 필요해요.
to connect to, so we're gonna create a deployment
연결할 파드가 필요하므로, 디플로이먼트를 생성한다.
with three replicas and it's just gonna run
세 개의 복제본과 함께 실행합니다.
the Apache web server.
아파치 웹 서버를 실행합니다.
So we do that.
그렇게 합니다.
Okay, cool.
좋아, 멋지네.
I can type.
타이핑할 수 있어요.
All right, good, we got our three pods up and running.
좋아, 세 개의 포드가 작동합니다.
Now we're going to go ahead and show the labels
이제 레이블을 표시해 보겠습니다.
on these pods.
이 포드에.
And when you create a deployment using that imperative
그리고 이 임퍼러티를 사용하여 디플로이먼트를 생성할 때
technique, which is that's just quick and dirty, right?
기법을 사용하면 빠르고 더럽지 않나요?
Normally you'd create a manifest, but when you use
보통은 매니페스트를 생성하지만, 다음과 같은 경우
that technique, you're gonna get a label, key, app
이 기법을 사용하면 레이블, 키, 앱을 얻게 됩니다.
and a value, which is the name of the deployment.
그리고 배포의 이름인 값을 얻게 됩니다.
So I can predict that, right?
이제 예측할 수 있겠죠?
I know I'm gonna have this app website label.
이 앱 웹사이트 라벨이 붙을 거라는 걸 알아요.
I don't know what the name of the pod's gonna be
포드 이름이 어떻게 될지 모르겠어요.
because they're ephemeral.
임시적이니까.
They come and go and they're identity lists, right?
그것들은 왔다가 사라지는 신원 목록이잖아요, 그렇죠?
I shouldn't care about the name, but I know that they're
이름은 신경 안 써도 되지만, 난 그들이
part of this website package.
이 웹사이트 패키지의 일부입니다.
All right, so the next thing I wanna do is I wanna create
좋아, 이제 다음으로 할 일은
a cluster IP service and we're gonna do this.
클러스터 IP 서비스를 만들어서 이렇게 하겠습니다.
This is basically the exact same service we just looked at
이것은 기본적으로 방금 살펴본 것과 똑같은 서비스입니다.
in the slides.
슬라이드에서.
All right, drop that in there.
좋아, 저기 넣어
All right.
됐어
kubectl get all, doesn't get everything, but it gets most
모든 것을 얻지는 못하지만 대부분을 얻는다.
of the stuff you care about.
관심 있는 것들만 가져온다.
So I got my three pods.
포드 세 개를 가져왔어요.
I have the replica set under the deployment.
디플로이먼트 아래에 레플리카 세트가 있다.
So the deployment created the replica set for me.
그래서 배포가 저를 위해 복제본 세트를 만들었습니다.
And then I've got my service website and it has a cluster IP
그리고 내 서비스 웹사이트에 클러스터 IP가 있습니다.
so that was handed to me by Kubernetes.
그래서 쿠버네티스가 저에게 전달한 것입니다.
Kubernetes decides what that's gonna be
쿠버네티스가 그 결과를 결정한다.
because Kubernetes has the service controller
쿠버네티스는 서비스 컨트롤러를 가지고 있기 때문이다.
and it also knows what the range of addresses
그리고 주소의 범위가 무엇인지도 알고 있다.
that you wanna use are.
가 무엇인지도 알고 있습니다.
Now, if we had used kubeadm with the config file
이제, 만약 우리가 구성 파일과 함께 kubeadm을 사용했다면
or given it the right command line parameters,
또는 올바른 커맨드 라인 파라미터를 제공했다면,
we get to change that to use something else if we wanted to.
원한다면 다른 것을 사용하도록 변경할 수 있습니다.
All right, so I'm gonna curl that and it works,
좋아, 이제 컬을 넣으면 작동합니다,
but I have no idea which pod I hit and I don't care.
하지만 어느 포드를 쳤는지도 모르겠고 신경도 안 써요.
They're all the same.
다 똑같아요.
They're replicas.
복제품입니다.
That's the point.
그게 요점입니다.
All right, so there's some other good stuff in here.
좋아, 여기 다른 좋은 것들이 있어.
And then the next thing that we're gonna do
그리고 다음에 우리가 할 일은
is we're gonna look for the range that Kubernetes is using.
쿠버네티스가 사용하는 범위를 찾을 것입니다.
So this is that service controller IP range, right?
이게 서비스 컨트롤러의 IP 범위 맞죠?
That's where the IP addresses are coming from
이것이 IP 주소가 오는 곳입니다.
for these services.
이 서비스를 위해.
So it's a 1096 stroke 12 is what the default is.
따라서 1096 스트로크 12가 기본값입니다.
You could change it.
변경할 수 있습니다.
Okay, a little bit more poking around
좋아, 조금만 더 들여다보자.
and now we're gonna look at some endpoints.
이제 몇 가지 엔드포인트를 살펴보겠습니다.
So let's take a look at the endpoints for the website.
이제 웹사이트의 엔드포인트를 살펴봅시다.
And we can see there's three of them, right?
세 개의 엔드포인트가 있는 것을 볼 수 있죠?
1015, 10154 and 1054.
1015, 10154, 1054.
And remember, they're always gonna have the same
그리고 기억하세요.
first three octets because the hosts are subnetted
호스트가 서브넷화되어 있기 때문에 처음 세 옥텟은
at 24 bits and then the overall space is eight bits.
24비트이고 전체 공간은 8비트입니다.
We saw that in CNI.
CNI에서 이를 확인했습니다.
So these are CNI controlled by Cilium
이것들은 실리움에 의해 제어되는 CNI입니다.
and then the service IP, the cluster IP
그리고 서비스 IP, 클러스터 IP인
is controlled by Kubernetes
은 쿠버네티스에 의해 제어된다.
because it's the service controller piece.
서비스 컨트롤러 부분이기 때문이다.
All right, good.
좋아요.
Let's see what else we got here.
또 뭐가 있는지 봅시다.
So the next thing we're gonna do
다음으로 할 일은 다음과 같습니다.
is try to figure out how this all works.
이 모든 것이 어떻게 작동하는지 알아내는 것입니다.
So we're gonna look into the IP tables
이제 IP 테이블을 살펴보겠습니다.
and we're gonna look for the cluster IP.
그리고 클러스터 IP를 찾겠습니다.
Obviously I can't use the one from the lab.
분명히 실험실의 것을 사용할 수 없습니다.
I have to use the one that I got
내가 가진 걸 써야겠어
which is potentially very different.
이는 잠재적으로 매우 다를 수 있습니다.
Service IPs aren't doled out sequentially
서비스 IP가 순차적으로 분배되지 않음
because then you could predict what the next one would be
다음 IP가 무엇인지 예측할 수 있기 때문입니다.
and that leaves you open to some security issues.
보안 문제가 발생할 수 있습니다.
So they're randomly selected from the range.
그래서 범위에서 무작위로 선택됩니다.
All right, so I can see that there's an IP tables rule
좋아, IP 테이블 규칙이 있음을 알 수 있습니다.
that says if TCP traffic comes from anywhere
TCP 트래픽이 어디에서 오든
and goes to that address on TCP port 80,
TCP 포트 80의 해당 주소로 이동합니다,
use that chain to figure out what happens.
이 체인을 사용하여 무슨 일이 일어나는지 알아보세요.
So the next thing I need to do
다음으로 해야 할 일은
is I need to update my grep
내 grep을 업데이트해야 합니다.
to look at the chain called this.
라는 체인을 살펴봅니다.
And...
그리고...
Let me actually...
내가 실제로...
Ah, yeah, there we go.
아, 그렇지.
And so that is pointing us at our service.
이제 우리 서비스를 가리키고 있습니다.
And you can see here, this guy says, all right,
여기 보시면, 이 남자가 이렇게 말합니다,
um, destination IP 80.
음, 목적지 IP 80.
Let's run this guy here.
이 녀석을 실행해 봅시다.
There we go.
됐어요.
And so those are the three pods
이렇게 세 개의 파드가 있습니다.
that we saw in our deployment.
배포에서 확인했습니다.
And you can see if you look at the packet counts,
패킷 수를 보면 알 수 있습니다,
you can of course tell which one you hit
물론 어느 쪽을 공격했는지 알 수 있습니다.
when you did your curl, right?
컬을 했을 때 말이죠?
It's this bottom guy as it turns out.
알고 보니 이 아랫사람이네.
So it's just a random probability,
그냥 무작위 확률입니다,
33% when there's three of them,
세 개가 있을 때 33%,
50% when there's two of them,
두 개일 때는 50%,
and then the last one's the default.
마지막 하나가 기본값이 됩니다.
And so this is the guy that got hit.
이 사람이 공격당한 사람입니다.
And so if I look for the pod that's 10.0.0.54,
그래서 파드를 찾으면 10.0.0.54입니다,
10.0.0.54,
and I look at that guy's logs, right?
저 남자의 로그를 보면, 그렇지?
So this is 54 down here.
여기가 54번지네요.
So let's look at the logs of this guy.
그럼 이 녀석의 로그를 살펴봅시다.
We'll see a bunch of stuff, but there's the hit, right?
여러 가지가 나오겠지만, 히트작이 있죠?
That was our curl.
저게 우리 컬이었어.
And then if we do this same thing and look at logs
그리고 동일한 작업을 수행하고 로그를 살펴보면 다음과 같습니다.
for anybody with the label app website, oh wow.
레이블 앱 웹사이트를 가진 사람이라면 누구나 알 수 있죠.
There we go.
됐어요.
We can see that there are no hits anywhere in here
여기 어디에도 히트가 없는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
except this one from our curl.
이 컬에서 나온 것만 빼고요.
So all three of the other pods, right?
그럼 다른 세 개의 파드도 모두 포함되는 거죠?
This guy, no hits.
이 녀석, 안 맞았어.
이 녀석, 적중 없음.
This guy got a hit.
이 녀석은 적중했습니다.
So the service is working, right?
서비스가 작동하는 거죠?
Our IP tables are solving the problem
IP 테이블이 문제를 해결하고 있습니다.
of randomly distributing traffic to our pods on the backend.
백엔드의 파드에 트래픽을 무작위로 분배하고 있습니다.
There's a little bit more exploration that goes on there.
조금 더 탐색이 진행 중입니다.
But that brings us down to the bottom section
하지만 이제 맨 아래 섹션으로 내려갑니다.
where we get to delete some things and see how stuff works.
여기서 몇 가지를 삭제하고 어떻게 작동하는지 확인할 수 있습니다.
So for example,
예를 들어
just gonna pick one of these guys at random and delete it.
이 중 하나를 무작위로 골라서 삭제합니다.
And a bunch of things happen when you do this.
이렇게 하면 여러 가지 일이 일어납니다.
Number one, the curl keeps working
첫째, 컬이 계속 작동합니다.
and you never even see any hesitation.
망설임이 전혀 보이지 않습니다.
And the reason is that the service proxy
그 이유는 서비스 프록시가
has taken the deleted pod out of the mesh.
가 삭제된 파드를 메시에서 제거했기 때문이다.
And of course, what also happens is that Kubernetes
물론, 쿠버네티스도 마찬가지다.
immediately realizes that there aren't three pods anymore.
는 더 이상 세 개의 파드가 없다는 것을 즉시 인식한다.
And since the replica set and the deployment
그리고 레플리카 세트와 디플로이먼트가 완료되었으므로
were set to have three, it creates a brand new one.
가 3개로 설정되었으므로, 새로운 것을 생성합니다.
It's not the same pod, right?
같은 포드가 아니죠?
That guy, if you look at the IP,
저 남자, IP를 보면,
right, not the same pod, right?
같은 포드 아니죠?
This guy is 134 and he's been running for 31 seconds
이 녀석은 134번이고 31초 동안 달렸어요.
versus the other guys, which are seven minutes.
다른 녀석들은 7분입니다.
So the mesh is dynamic, right?
메시가 동적이지 않나요?
It's taking advantage of this dynamic environment
이 동적인 환경을 활용하고 있습니다.
and automatically updating all of the routing
모든 라우팅을 자동으로 업데이트합니다.
or forwarding necessary to make things go.
또는 라우팅에 필요한 포워딩을 수행합니다.
All right, so let's move on.
좋아, 그럼 계속 진행하자.
And keep in mind, if you're done with two before I move on,
그리고 명심해, 내가 넘어가기 전에 두 개 다 끝내야 해,
feel free to move on yourself.
자유롭게 계속 진행하세요.
All right, so Kubernetes DNS.
자, 쿠버네티스 DNS.
Let's talk about DNS briefly
DNS에 대해 간단히 이야기해보자.
and how Kubernetes implements it.
그리고 쿠버네티스가 어떻게 구현하는지 알아보자.
If you're still working on lab two, keep working,
아직 실습 2를 진행 중이라면 계속 진행하세요,
just lend me half an ear.
귀를 반만 빌려줘.
So DNS and Kubernetes, there are three files
DNS와 쿠버네티스에는 세 개의 파일이 있다.
that your containers get
컨테이너가 받는
that come from the container runtime,
컨테이너 런타임에서 온다,
not from your image, your container image.
이미지가 아닌 컨테이너 이미지에서 온 것입니다.
They're always overlaid by the container runtime.
항상 컨테이너 런타임에 의해 오버레이됩니다.
And the reason is if you take a HTTP container
그 이유는 HTTP 컨테이너에서
and you run it in Singapore, it's gonna get one IP.
싱가포르에서 실행하면 하나의 IP를 얻게 됩니다.
If you run it in London, it's gonna get another IP.
런던에서 실행하면 다른 IP를 얻게 됩니다.
So how could you possibly create an Etsy host file
그렇다면 어떻게 Etsy 호스트 파일을 만들 수 있을까요?
with the correct information, right?
올바른 정보로 만들 수 있죠?
Since it should have your IP and your host name in there.
내 IP와 호스트 이름이 들어가야 하니까요.
How could you possibly create a host name file
어떻게 호스트 이름 파일을 만들 수 있죠?
with the correct information since the name of your host
호스트 이름 이후 올바른 정보로 수정합니다.
when you're a pod is the name of your pod?
파드라면 파드의 이름인가?
And that's dynamically being created.
그리고 그것은 동적으로 생성되고 있다.
So you don't even know what it's gonna be.
그래서 당신은 그것이 어떻게 될지조차 모릅니다.
And then the final thing is resolve.conf.
그리고 마지막은 resolve.conf입니다.
Every Kubernetes cluster runs core DNS by default.
모든 쿠버네티스 클러스터는 기본적으로 코어 DNS를 실행한다.
Some distros change it and use something else
일부 배포판은 이를 변경하여 다른 것을 사용한다.
and some distros configure core DNS in different ways.
일부 배포판은 코어 DNS를 다른 방식으로 구성합니다.
But there is a DNS server built into Kubernetes.
하지만 쿠버네티스에는 DNS 서버가 내장되어 있다.
And when you use the reference installer,
그리고 레퍼런스 인스톨러를 사용하면
kube-adm, you get core DNS, which is another CNCF project,
kube-adm을 사용하면 또 다른 CNCF 프로젝트인 코어 DNS를 얻게 된다,
one of the earliest ones.
가장 빠른 것 중 하나이다.
And so core DNS will automatically resolve service names
따라서 코어 DNS는 자동으로 서비스 이름을 확인합니다.
inside your cluster to their virtual IPs
클러스터 내부의 가상 IP로
so that you can just use names instead of IPs,
따라서 IP 대신 이름만 사용할 수 있습니다,
which is great.
아주 좋습니다.
But that means those three files
하지만 이는 다음 세 파일을 의미합니다.
have to be correctly configured.
을 올바르게 설정해야 합니다.
And so it's the kubelet
그리고 이것이 바로 kubelet이다.
that understands your Kubernetes environment
쿠버네티스 환경을 이해한다.
and sets these files up so that your pod works.
파드가 작동하도록 이 파일들을 설정한다.
And so you have core DNS running
이제 코어 DNS가 실행된다.
in the kube system namespace.
을 실행합니다.
As you can see up here, we have two pods, core DNS pods.
여기에서 볼 수 있듯이, 코어 DNS 파드인 두 개의 파드가 있습니다.
So if one of them crashes, we have resilience, right?
둘 중 하나가 충돌해도 복원력이 있는 거죠?
Kubernetes eats its own dog food.
쿠버네티스는 스스로 개밥을 먹는다.
Core DNS runs in a deployment.
코어 DNS가 디플로이먼트에서 실행된다.
And then there's a service also
그리고 서비스도 있습니다.
that gives us a cluster IP for DNS inside Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스 내부의 DNS를 위한 클러스터 IP를 제공한다.
And it's 10.96.0.10.
그리고 10.96.0.10입니다.
That's the default IP for DNS.
이것이 DNS의 기본 IP입니다.
And it's gonna be injected into every single pod
그리고 모든 단일 파드에 주입될 것입니다.
in resolve.conf.
resolve.conf에.
Because when your pod tries to look up a name,
왜냐하면 파드가 이름을 조회하려고 할 때,
it needs to go to core DNS to find the IP of that service.
이면 코어 DNS로 이동하여 해당 서비스의 IP를 찾아야 한다.
We don't generally look at pods, right?
우리는 일반적으로 파드를 보지 않죠?
They're ephemeral.
일시적이잖아요.
We don't care about them.
우리는 그들에 대해 신경 쓰지 않습니다.
We care about the API that we're trying to consume, right?
우리는 우리가 사용하려는 API가 중요하지 않나요?
The interface, not the implementation.
구현이 아니라 인터페이스가 중요하죠.
And so that's a quick look at core DNS
핵심 DNS를 간략히 살펴보면 다음과 같습니다.
and how it's set up and what it does.
그리고 설정 방법과 기능에 대해 알아보겠습니다.
And then if you want to think about DNS inside a cluster,
그리고 클러스터 내부의 DNS에 대해 생각해 보겠습니다,
number one, you might have many clusters.
첫째, 많은 클러스터가 있을 수 있습니다.
So you can give every single cluster its own suffix, right?
그럼 모든 클러스터에 고유한 접미사를 부여할 수 있겠죠?
Cluster.local is the default.
Cluster.local이 기본값입니다.
And so you get cluster.local
그래서 클러스터.local을 얻는다.
in the example we're gonna look at.
이 예제에서 살펴볼 것이다.
Next, there's the service bucket where services live.
다음으로, 서비스가 있는 서비스 버킷이 있습니다.
There's some other buckets,
다른 버킷도 있습니다,
but this is the most important one.
하지만 이것이 가장 중요한 버킷입니다.
And then namespaces are a thing in Kubernetes, right?
그리고 쿠버네티스에서는 네임스페이스가 중요하죠?
If I want dev and production,
만약 내가 개발과 프로덕션을 원한다면,
if I want team A and team B,
팀 A와 팀 B를 원한다면
if I want blue, green, whatever,
파란색, 녹색, 뭐든 원하는 경우,
different namespaces are isolated from each other.
서로 다른 네임스페이스가 서로 격리되어 있습니다.
And so if you create a service called Fred
따라서 프레드라는 서비스를 만들면
and I try to create one and I get an error,
를 만들려고 하면 오류가 발생합니다,
that's gonna be confusing, right?
혼란스럽지 않나요?
If we're in completely different departments and contexts
완전히 다른 부서와 상황에 있는 경우
and we don't even normally talk to each other,
평소에는 서로 대화도 하지 않는 경우,
that's gonna be a big problem.
큰 문제가 될 거야.
So namespaces give you the ability
네임스페이스는 다음과 같은 기능을 제공합니다.
to create any name you want,
원하는 이름을 만들 수 있습니다,
which means the DNS has to be isolated.
즉, DNS를 격리해야 합니다.
And so the namespace is in the DNS name.
따라서 네임스페이스는 DNS 이름에 있습니다.
And then finally you have the name of the service itself.
그리고 마지막으로 서비스 자체의 이름이 있습니다.
So an example of a realistic production DNS name
실제 프로덕션 DNS 이름의 예는 다음과 같습니다.
for a service in Kubernetes might be web,
은 웹일 수 있다,
if your service is called web,
이 될 수 있다,
production, if your namespace is called production,
네임스페이스가 프로덕션인 경우 프로덕션,
.svc and then k8s54.rx-m.com,
.svc, 그리고 k8s54.rx-m.com입니다,
if that's the suffix you gave that cluster.
이 클러스터에 지정한 접미사인 경우.
And so you can see with this kind of a unique name,
이런 종류의 고유 이름을 사용하면 알 수 있습니다,
I can actually reach a service
실제로 서비스에 연결할 수 있습니다.
in a completely different cluster, right?
완전히 다른 클러스터에 있는 거죠?
I could give the name of the service,
서비스 이름을 알려줄 수 있어요,
the namespace in the cluster,
클러스터의 네임스페이스,
the SVC and then the cluster suffix.
그리고 클러스터 접미사.
And as long as my networking,
그리고 내 네트워킹이 작동하는 한,
normal computer networking infrastructure
일반 컴퓨터 네트워킹 인프라
knows how to deliver that packet to that cluster,
해당 패킷을 해당 클러스터로 전달하는 방법을 알고 있습니다,
we've got connectivity.
연결되었습니다.
So headless services are another thing.
헤드리스 서비스는 또 다른 문제입니다.
We mentioned if you say cluster IP none,
클러스터 IP가 없다고 하면 언급했습니다,
you'll get a headless service.
헤드리스 서비스를 받게 됩니다.
Well, what happens in a headless service?
헤드리스 서비스에서는 어떤 일이 일어나나요?
In a headless service, you don't want the cluster IP,
헤드리스 서비스에서는 클러스터 IP를 원하지 않습니다,
you don't wanna look that up,
를 조회하고 싶지 않을 것입니다,
cause it's no good, right?
안 좋은 거니까, 그치?
You don't wanna randomly go somewhere.
무작정 어딘가로 가고 싶지 않을 거야.
If I want New York data,
뉴욕 데이터를 원한다면,
I have to talk to that Kafka node.
카프카 노드와 대화해야 합니다.
If I want life data, I gotta talk to that Kafka node.
생명 데이터를 원한다면, 저 카프카 노드와 대화해야 합니다.
So in a headless service,
그래서 헤드리스 서비스에서,
you get the actual IPs of all of the nodes
모든 노드의 실제 IP를 얻게 됩니다.
or all the pods when you look up the service name.
또는 서비스 이름을 조회할 때 모든 파드의 IP를 얻을 수 있다.
So it's not just one IP of the head of the cluster IP,
따라서 클러스터 헤드의 IP가 하나만 있는 것이 아닙니다,
you're gonna get all the pod IPs together.
모든 파드 IP를 모을 것이다.
The other thing that is important
또 다른 중요한 것은
is that there's a special controller for stateful pods
스테이트풀 파드를 위한 특별한 컨트롤러가 있다는 것이다.
called a stateful set.
스테이트풀 세트라고 한다.
And it creates pods with deterministic names,
그리고 결정론적 이름을 가진 파드를 생성한다,
with identity, with persistent identity.
아이덴티티를 가진, 영구적인 아이덴티티를 가진 파드를 생성한다.
If this pod, which is let's call it web7,
이 파드를 웹7이라고 하자,
gets evicted from a computer,
컴퓨터에서 쫓겨난다,
we won't get web58 over here,
웹58이 여기로 들어오지 않습니다,
we'll get web7 again over here.
웹7을 다시 가져옵니다.
Might have a different IP,
다른 IP가 있을 수 있습니다,
but the name will be the same.
하지만 이름은 동일합니다.
So if you create a stateful set of Redis,
따라서 Redis의 스테이트풀 집합을 생성하면,
the pods will be called Redis0, Redis1, Redis2,
파드는 Redis0, Redis1, Redis2라고 불릴 것이다,
with an ordinal as they get created.
생성될 때 서수를 사용한다.
So you can predict the name
따라서 이름을 예측할 수 있습니다.
and that name will be persistent, it won't go away.
그리고 그 이름은 사라지지 않고 지속될 것입니다.
In other words, the Kafka guy
다시 말해, 카프카라는 사람은
that's servicing the NASDAQ market data,
나스닥 시장 데이터를 서비스하고 있습니다,
when it crashes, it's gonna fire back up over here
충돌하면 이쪽에서 다시 시작됩니다.
and it's gonna still be Kafka7 with the NASDAQ data.
여전히 나스닥 데이터와 함께 카프카7이 있을 겁니다.
And the volume it was using is gonna chase it.
그리고 사용하던 볼륨이 그것을 쫓아갈 것입니다.
And it's network-attachable.
그리고 네트워크에 연결할 수 있습니다.
So that's what we want in a stateful set.
이것이 바로 우리가 스테이트풀 세트에서 원하는 것입니다.
And so if I need to look up Kafka7,
그래서 만약 제가 카프카7을 조회해야 한다면요,
I don't wanna fix myself on the IP.
IP에 집착하고 싶지 않아요.
What if it gets punted to a new machine
새 컴퓨터로 전송되면 어떻게 하죠?
and gets a different IP?
다른 IP를 얻으면?
I wanna use the DNS name, right?
DNS 이름을 사용하고 싶지 않나요?
I wanna be abstract from the machinery of the networking.
나는 네트워킹의 기계로부터 추상화되고 싶다.
And so I could say, hey, Redis1.redis.datans,
그래서 저는 이렇게 말할 수 있죠, Redis1.redis.datans,
which is my namespace, service cluster local,
내 네임스페이스, 서비스 클러스터 로컬입니다,
let's say that's the guy who has the NASDAQ data,
이 사람이 나스닥 데이터를 가진 사람이라고 가정해 봅시다,
then I would just connect to that guy every time.
그러면 저는 매번 그 사람에게 연결할 것입니다.
And I would always get the NASDAQ data.
그리고 저는 항상 나스닥 데이터를 얻었습니다.
So that's what a headless service brings to the table.
이것이 바로 헤드리스 서비스의 장점입니다.
It creates this DNS structure for stateful pods.
스테이트풀 파드를 위한 이 DNS 구조를 생성합니다.
And generally, that's why you use a headless service
일반적으로 헤드리스 서비스를 사용하는 이유는 다음과 같다.
when you have stateful pods.
스테이트풀 파드가 있을 때.
So overriding the DNS is also possible.
따라서 DNS를 재정의하는 것도 가능하다.
What if you're an administrator and you have to run a pod
관리자가 파드를 실행해야 하는 경우 어떻게 해야 하나요?
and that pod needs to talk to an external DNS system?
해당 파드가 외부 DNS 시스템과 통신해야 한다면?
You don't want it going to the internal one,
내부로 가는 것을 원하지 않는다,
you wanna go into the external one.
외부로 가고 싶어.
You can set up your resolve.conf as custom as you like.
resolve.conf를 원하는 대로 설정할 수 있습니다.
A resolve.conf is generally gonna have a name server
resolve.conf에는 일반적으로 다음과 같은 네임 서버가 있습니다.
to connect to, searches, so suffixes that you would add.
연결할 네임 서버, 검색, 접미사를 추가할 수 있습니다.
If I look for web, it's gonna work.
웹을 찾으면 작동합니다.
Why?
왜?
Because there's a suffix in there that is gonna specify
왜냐면 거기에 접미사가 있어서
mynamespace.service.whatever my cluster suffix is.
내 클러스터 접미사가 뭐든간에.
I can just look up the service and it works.
서비스를 조회하면 작동합니다.
If I wanna look up a service in another namespace,
다른 네임스페이스에서 서비스를 조회하고 싶은 경우,
I can just say service.othernamespace and it will work
서비스닷오너스페이스라고 하면 작동합니다.
because there's multiple search paths
여러 검색 경로가 있기 때문입니다.
for each piece of the DNS name.
의 각 부분에 대해
And then finally you have options that you can set.
마지막으로 설정할 수 있는 옵션이 있습니다.
So this is, if you're not a DNS guru, you can ignore this,
DNS 전문가가 아니라면 무시해도 됩니다,
but basically these are the ways that you can override
하지만 기본적으로 다음과 같은 방법으로 재정의할 수 있습니다.
what's in the resolve.conf.
resolve.conf에 있는 내용.
So step three, playing around with DNS.
3단계, DNS를 가지고 노는 단계입니다.
Let's give everybody, let's say until 10 after
모든 사람에게 10시 이후까지 시간을 주자.
to work through that.
시간을 주자.
Seven minutes.
7분 남았습니다.
Again, go ahead and work on your own.
다시 한번, 혼자서 작업하세요.
I'm just gonna, for the virtual folks
난 그냥 가상 사람들을 위해
and for people who don't have a laptop,
그리고 노트북이 없는 사람들을 위해,
I'll just give you a preview here.
여기서 미리 알려드리겠습니다.
So let's see, did I clean up after myself last time?
어디 보자, 내가 지난번에 청소는 했나?
I did not.
안 했어.
Let me go ahead and do that.
내가 할게.
So I'm gonna kudos delete some stuff real quick.
몇 개만 빨리 삭제할게요.
All right, so on the DNS side,
좋아, 그럼 DNS 쪽에서,
we're gonna create a deployment again.
배포를 다시 생성하겠습니다.
So.
그럼.
And then we're gonna expose it.
그리고 우리는 그것을 폭로할 것이다.
This is a cheeky way to create a service.
이것은 서비스를 만드는 건방진 방법입니다.
All right, it creates a service
좋아, 서비스를 생성합니다.
that's wired to that deployment,
해당 배포에 연결된 서비스를 생성합니다,
so it figures out what labels to use automatically.
그래서 어떤 레이블을 사용할지 자동으로 알아냅니다.
And now I'm going to run a client,
이제 클라이언트를 실행해 보겠습니다,
and we're gonna look around at how we can resolve the name
그리고 어떻게 이름을 확인할 수 있는지 살펴볼 것입니다.
instead of the IP.
를 입력합니다.
So BusyBox image has to download.
따라서 BusyBox 이미지를 다운로드해야 합니다.
We'll let it do that.
그렇게 하도록 놔두겠습니다.
And the idea is, let's just try first to W,
일단 W로 먼저 시도해 봅시다,
there's no curl in BusyBox, so we'll W get the website.
BusyBox에 컬이 없으므로 웹사이트를 W로 가져옵니다.
And we're gonna, this is DNS, right?
여기가 DNS 맞죠?
I'm saying, hey, look up website.
이봐, 웹사이트를 찾아봐.
I mean, how does that work, right?
그게 어떻게 작동하죠?
How does that work?
어떻게 작동하죠?
It works, but how does it work?
작동하지만 어떻게 작동하죠?
Well, let's take a look at the DNS machinery.
그럼, DNS 메커니즘을 살펴봅시다.
All right, the first thing that we would wanna do
좋아요, 가장 먼저 할 일은
is look at the resolve.conf.
resolve.conf를 살펴보는 것입니다.
Right, whenever your resolver,
네, 리졸버가
the part of the Linux library or the, you know,
리눅스 라이브러리의 일부이거나,
the glibc or whatever it is that's doing your resolution,
해상도를 높이는 glibc나 뭐든 간에요,
it's probably going to a cache.
아마 캐시로 가고 있을 겁니다.
If it doesn't see the name there,
거기에 이름이 보이지 않는다면,
then it's looking in your atc host.
이면 atc 호스트에서 찾고 있는 것입니다.
If it doesn't see the name there, then it's going to DNS.
이름이 표시되지 않으면 DNS로 이동하는 것입니다.
So where does it find the DNS server?
그러면 어디에서 DNS 서버를 찾을까요?
Well, there you go, myresolve.conf.
자, 여기 myresolve.conf가 있습니다.
Recognize that IP?
이 IP 알아보시겠어요?
It's 10.96.0.1.
10.96.0.1입니다.
That's our core DNS service.
이것이 우리의 핵심 DNS 서비스입니다.
It's the cluster IP of our core DNS.
코어 DNS의 클러스터 IP입니다.
Kubernetes eats its own dog food.
쿠버네티스가 자신의 개밥을 먹는다.
Then look at the search suffixes.
그런 다음 검색 접미사를 살펴본다.
I'm in the default namespace on cluster.local.
저는 cluster.local의 기본 네임스페이스에 있습니다.
So when you make the name, right,
그래서 이름을 만들 때, 맞습니다,
if you fully qualify it and you say .default,
완전히 정규화하고 .default라고 하면,
.service, .cluster, .local, right,
.service, .cluster, .local, 오른쪽,
that's what's happening, right?
이게 무슨 일이지?
We're just adding that search suffix
검색 접미사만 추가하면 됩니다.
and it's a fully qualified name.
정규화된 이름입니다.
It won't conflict with website services
웹사이트 서비스와 충돌하지 않습니다.
and other namespaces.
및 다른 네임스페이스와 충돌하지 않습니다.
What if I want to get to a website service
웹사이트 서비스로 이동하려면 어떻게 해야 하나요?
in another namespace?
다른 네임스페이스에 있나요?
Well, you can, right?
할 수 있죠?
You can simply say website.prod, let's say.
웹사이트.prod라고 하면 됩니다.
Now that's not going to work
이제 작동하지 않습니다.
because I don't have a prod namespace,
프로드 네임스페이스가 없으니까요,
but you can see it doesn't work, right?
하지만 작동하지 않는다는 것을 알 수 있죠?
It would have worked if it was in default,
기본값이었다면 작동했을 겁니다,
but you said go look in prod and there isn't one there.
하지만 프로드를 찾아보라고 했는데 거기에는 없습니다.
And so notice that this guy was resolving
그래서 이 사람이 다음을 해결하고 있었음을 알 수 있습니다.
with service.cluster.local, the second search, right,
두 번째 검색인 service.cluster.local로요,
suffix, and then we have cluster.local
접미사를 추가하고, 그 다음에는 클러스터.local
and then whatever gets inherited from the host machines.
그리고 호스트 머신에서 무엇이든 상속받습니다.
All right, cool.
좋아, 멋지네.
So we now have the idea of like how the pod side
이제 파드 측에서 다음과 같은 아이디어를 얻었습니다.
of it's working, right?
작동하고 있는 거죠?
And I'm just going to exit out of this guy.
이제 이 녀석에서 빠져나갈게요.
And if we do a kubectl get all
그리고 만약 우리가 kubectl을 실행하면
in the namespace kubecystem,
네임스페이스 kubecystem에서,
you know, there's the machinery, right?
기계가 있잖아, 그렇지?
In kubecystem, we have the core DNS deployment
쿠버시스템에는 핵심 DNS 배포가 있다.
with two pods and we have our replica set
두 개의 파드가 있고 레플리카 세트가 있다.
and we have the two pods up there.
저 위에 두 개의 파드가 있습니다.
And then there's the core DNS service.
그리고 핵심 DNS 서비스가 있습니다.
So those are the pieces of the puzzle.
이것이 퍼즐의 조각입니다.
All right, and the lab goes on and it has you play
자, 이제 실험은 계속되고, 여러분은
around a little bit with some of this stuff.
이걸로 좀 놀아보자.
Then it has you create a headless service.
그런 다음 헤드리스 서비스를 만들게 합니다.
Got a couple of minutes, I might do that real quick.
몇 분 남았으니 빨리 해볼게요.
So I'm going to go ahead and create this headless service.
그럼 이제 이 헤드리스 서비스를 만들어볼게요.
The special thing about the headless service
헤드리스 서비스의 특별한 점
over a normal service is that it has no cluster IP.
일반 서비스에 비해 특별한 점은 클러스터 IP가 없다는 것입니다.
And so you can see at the bottom here, cluster IP none.
그래서 여기 하단에 클러스터 IP가 없는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
All right, and then the lab has us take a look
자, 이제 실험실에서 다음을 살펴봅니다.
at the cluster IP service.
클러스터 IP 서비스에서.
We see that he's got no cluster IP.
클러스터 IP가 없음을 알 수 있습니다.
And then we're going to jump back into that pod
그리고 다시 해당 파드로 이동합니다.
and we're going to do some NS lookups to see
그리고 NS 조회를 수행하여 다음을 확인합니다.
what kind of DNS trouble we can get into.
어떤 종류의 DNS 문제가 발생할 수 있는지 확인합니다.
So I'm going to kubectl attach my input stream
그래서 나는 내 입력 스트림을 kubectl에 첨부한다.
to what was it called, client.
클라이언트라는 이름의 스트림에 연결한다.
Client, there we go, okay.
클라이언트, 알겠습니다.
And so let's go ahead and try that NS lookup
이제 NS 조회를 시도해 보겠습니다.
on headless website that we just created.
방금 만든 헤드리스 웹사이트에서요.
And you can see, I don't get back a single IP,
보시다시피, 하나의 IP도 반환되지 않습니다,
I get back all of them.
전부 다 돌아옵니다.
There's three pods, I get all three of them.
세 개의 포드가 있는데, 세 개를 모두 가져옵니다.
And some DNS errors, but you get the idea, right?
그리고 몇 가지 DNS 오류도 있지만, 무슨 말인지 아시겠죠?
So the lookup worked, we got the three pods.
조회는 성공했고, 세 개의 파드를 얻었습니다.
And you can see that these three pods,
그리고 이 세 개의 파드를 볼 수 있습니다,
they don't have unique identity.
고유한 정체성을 가지고 있지 않음을 알 수 있다.
They're created by a deployment, they have random names.
배포에 의해 생성되며 임의의 이름을 가집니다.
And so we just, hey, here are the IP addresses,
여기 IP 주소가 있습니다,
if you want to connect to one, you can.
이 중 하나에 연결하고 싶으면 연결할 수 있습니다.
But the idea then is to take this to the next level
하지만 다음 단계로 넘어가야 합니다.
where we put the headless service on top of a stateful set.
헤드리스 서비스를 스테이트풀 세트 위에 올려놓는 것입니다.
So that's this guy down here.
여기 이 녀석입니다.
Note that a YAML file can have multiple YAML documents.
한 개의 YAML 파일에 여러 개의 YAML 문서가 있을 수 있다는 점에 유의하세요.
And that's exactly what's going on in here.
이것이 바로 여기서 일어나고 있는 일입니다.
We have the first part is our service, right?
첫 번째 부분은 우리 서비스죠?
So that's just the service without the cluster IP, right?
클러스터 IP가 없는 서비스만 있는 거죠?
The headless service, and then this is the stateful set.
헤드리스 서비스, 그리고 이것은 스테이트풀 세트입니다.
We're saying, hey, we're going to pretend
이봐요, 우리는 마치
that these nginx guys are actually stateful.
이 nginx 녀석들이 실제로 상태 저장소인 것처럼 말이죠.
They're not, but it's all right.
그렇지 않지만 괜찮아요.
And now let's, cube CTO apply minus F, that guy.
이제 큐브 CTO가 마이너스 F를 적용해 봅시다.
Now what we can see is we have the,
이제 우리가 볼 수 있는 것은,
we've got this new stateful set called web state, right?
웹 상태라는 새로운 상태 저장 집합이 생겼죠?
And that web state has created a pod, web state zero.
그리고 그 웹 스테이트가 파드인 웹 스테이트 제로를 생성했다.
So the pod gets the name of the stateful set
그래서 파드는 스테이트풀 세트의 이름을 얻는다.
plus an ordinal, and if I cube CTL scale,
에 서수를 더하고, CTL 스케일을 큐브화하면,
stateful set web state to replicas equal three,
상태 저장 웹 상태를 복제본으로 설정하면 3이 됩니다,
you got to spell it right.
철자를 제대로 써야 합니다.
Fortunately, there's a shortcut.
다행히도 지름길이 있습니다.
All right, so that's scaled.
자, 이제 크기가 조정되었습니다.
Now there we go, right?
이제 됐죠?
Zero, one and two.
0, 1, 2
So if we go back up and attach again to our previous guy,
다시 올라가서 이전 녀석에게 다시 연결합니다,
and then we nslookup web state,
그리고 웹 상태를 조회합니다,
let's just do that.
그냥 해봅시다.
You can see that we get the lookup as always, right?
언제나처럼 조회가 되는 것을 볼 수 있지요?
Web state is in fact a service,
웹 상태는 실제로 서비스입니다,
but now what we can do is we can ask
하지만 이제 우리가 할 수 있는 것은 다음과 같이 물어볼 수 있습니다.
for a different kind of query.
다른 종류의 쿼리를 요청할 수 있습니다.
You can ask for an SRV query.
SRV 쿼리를 요청할 수 있습니다.
Is it equal?
동일합니까?
There we go.
됐어요.
And you can see that over here, web state zero, one and two.
여기 웹 상태 0, 1, 2를 볼 수 있습니다.
So we can identify these guys now
이제 이 녀석들을 식별할 수 있습니다.
by their actual names.
그들의 실제 이름으로.
And if we try to, for example, curl a specific one of them,
예를 들어 그중 특정 하나를 컬링하려고 하면 다음과 같습니다,
we can say web state,
웹 상태라고 할 수 있습니다,
I want to talk to specifically the NASDAQ guy, right?
특히 나스닥 담당자와 얘기하고 싶어요, 그렇죠?
Because I don't want the New York Stock Exchange data.
뉴욕 증권 거래소 데이터는 필요 없으니까요.
I want the NASDAQ guy, and he's number one.
난 나스닥에 있는 사람이 필요해, 그가 1등이야.
And curl's not found, so I'll use wget.
curl을 찾을 수 없으니 wget을 사용하겠습니다.
And there you go, right?
이제 됐죠?
We hit the NGINX guy there.
저기 NGINX 놈을 공격했어.
So that's DNS in its various flavors in Kubernetes, right?
이게 바로 쿠버네티스의 다양한 버전의 DNS죠?
And of course, I mean, as you guys know,
물론, 여러분도 아시다시피,
there's a lot more to know,
알아야 할 게 더 많아요,
but the lab does start you down the road,
하지만 실험실에서 출발할 수 있어요,
hopefully is pulling away the veil
희망은 베일을 벗기고 있다
on some of the more confusing bits
좀 더 혼란스러운 부분들
and the things that aren't obvious when you start off.
그리고 처음 시작할 때 명확하지 않은 것들.
All right, so let's move into our next section,
자, 이제 다음 섹션으로 넘어가죠,
accessing services from the outside.
외부에서 서비스에 액세스합니다.
How do we get from the outside in?
외부에서 어떻게 들어가나요?
Keep working on the labs if you want.
원한다면 실험실에서 계속 작업하세요.
Let me in here.
들여보내줘.
So outside access can be performed in lots of ways.
외부 접속은 여러 가지 방법으로 할 수 있습니다.
At the end of the day, there's host port and node port,
결국 호스트 포트와 노드 포트가 있습니다,
and a lot of stuff on top of them.
그리고 그 위에 많은 것들이 있습니다.
Host port and node port handle 99.99%
호스트 포트와 노드 포트가 99.99%를 처리합니다.
of the traffic flowing into a cluster,
클러스터로 유입되는 트래픽의 비율입니다,
one of those two techniques.
이 두 가지 기술 중 하나입니다.
So what does a host port do?
그렇다면 호스트 포트는 무엇을 할까요?
It's not a service.
서비스가 아닙니다.
In a pod, you can say, take this port on the host
파드에서, 호스트에서 이 포트를 가져가라고 말할 수 있다.
and map it to the pod's listening port, right?
를 파드의 리스닝 포트에 매핑하면 되겠죠?
And that will work.
그러면 작동합니다.
The problem with that is it's not very friendly
문제는 그다지 친숙하지 않다는 겁니다.
to the cluster, right?
클러스터로 이동하는 거죠?
If you want to map port 80 on the host, I mean, good luck.
호스트에서 포트 80을 매핑하려면 행운을 빕니다.
What if none of the hosts have port 80 open?
포트 80이 열려있는 호스트가 하나도 없다면?
Your pod can't run anywhere.
파드가 아무데도 실행될 수 없다.
So it's not a great solution for your users,
따라서 사용자에게 좋은 솔루션이 아니다,
for us developers who are trying to deploy apps, right?
앱을 배포하려는 우리 개발자들에게는요?
You don't wanna use a host port.
호스트 포트를 사용하고 싶지 않으세요?
It's for administrators, right?
관리자용이죠?
If I'm running SSH in a pod, well, yeah,
만약 내가 파드에서 SSH를 실행하고 있다면, 네, 맞아요,
I want it to listen on 22,
22에 수신하기를 원한다,
so I might host port that or something
그래서 그 포트를 호스트할 수도 있고
for diagnostics or testing,
진단이나 테스트를 위해,
but it's not for general use for users, right?
하지만 사용자가 일반적으로 사용하는 것은 아니죠?
What users should be using is a node port.
사용자가 사용해야 하는 것은 노드 포트입니다.
A node port's a service, and it's a cluster IP.
노드 포트는 서비스이며 클러스터 IP입니다.
You get a cluster IP, right?
클러스터 IP를 받았죠?
It's like an inheritance hierarchy, right?
상속 계층 구조 같은 거죠?
Cluster IP is the base class,
클러스터 IP가 베이스 클래스입니다,
and node port is a derived class.
노드 포트는 파생 클래스입니다.
All the cluster IP stuff you get,
모든 클러스터 IP 정보입니다,
plus a port is selected from the node port range,
노드 포트 범위에서 포트가 선택됩니다,
like let's say 310, right?
예를 들어 310이라고 치죠?
Three, three zero zero one zero, so 30,010, I guess,
3, 3, 3, 0, 0, 0, 그러니까 30,010이네요,
and that's your port,
그게 네 포트야
and every single host computer will now take traffic
이제 모든 호스트 컴퓨터가 트래픽을 받습니다.
on that port and forward it to your service.
의 트래픽을 받아 서비스로 전달합니다.
So if you set up, for example, a load balancer
예를 들어 로드 밸런서를 다음과 같이 설정하면 됩니다.
in front of all the nodes in your cluster
클러스터의 모든 노드 앞에서
and direct traffic to that port,
해당 포트로 트래픽을 유도합니다,
you will be reaching your service,
서비스에 도달하게 됩니다,
and that's exactly what a load balancer service does.
이것이 바로 로드밸런서 서비스가 하는 일입니다.
So the inheritance hierarchy continues.
상속 계층 구조가 계속 이어집니다.
Cluster IP, node port, load balancer.
클러스터 IP, 노드 포트, 로드밸런서.
The node balancer, load balancer is the most derived, right?
노드 밸런서, 로드 밸런서가 가장 많이 파생된 것 맞죠?
It is a node port, and it is a cluster IP.
노드 포트이고, 클러스터 IP입니다.
So inside the cluster, you can use the cluster IP.
따라서 클러스터 내부에서는 클러스터 IP를 사용할 수 있습니다.
That's best.
그게 최선입니다.
It's DNS resolvable.
DNS 확인 가능.
It's gonna load balance you.
로드 밸런스를 맞추겠습니다.
It's fast.
빠르네.
Then node port, that's one hop, right?
그럼 노드 포트는 한 홉이죠?
You go right to the pod.
바로 파드로 이동합니다.
Node port is two hops, right?
노드 포트는 두 홉이죠?
Because you have to first hit the port on the host,
호스트의 포트에 먼저 접속해야 하기 때문입니다,
and somebody's got to forward your traffic
그리고 누군가는 당신의 트래픽을 전달해야 합니다.
to the next hop, right?
다음 홉으로 전달해야 하죠?
There are scenarios where you can have actually
실제로 다음과 같은 시나리오가 있을 수 있습니다.
a user mode proxy, like kube-proxy,
사용자 모드 프록시를 사용할 수 있다,
and some versions of Kubernetes will actually listen
그리고 일부 쿠버네티스 버전은 실제로 수신한다.
on all the node ports and forward the traffic.
를 수신하고 트래픽을 전달한다.
In other cases, it's handled by the kernel,
다른 경우에는 커널이 처리합니다,
the eBPF and stuff like that.
에 의해 처리됩니다.
But then ultimately, your traffic ends up being delivered
하지만 궁극적으로 트래픽이 전달됩니다.
to the pod, and the pod's probably not on that computer,
로 전달되고 파드는 해당 컴퓨터에 없을 것입니다,
right, unless you know specifically
그래, 네가 구체적으로 알지 못한다면
if there's 100 computers in the cluster,
클러스터에 100대의 컴퓨터가 있는 경우,
and you're running five pods,
그리고 5개의 파드를 실행하고 있다,
you're only running on 5% of the nodes.
5%의 노드에서만 실행하고 있다.
If you pick a host and hit the node port,
호스트를 선택하고 노드 포트를 누르면,
chances are your pod's not on that node.
파드가 해당 노드에 있지 않을 가능성이 있다.
So you're gonna have two hops, right?
그럼 두 홉이 있는 거죠?
You're gonna hit the host, and then it's gonna have
호스트에 부딪히면, 호스트가
to forward your traffic over to the machine
트래픽을 기계로 전달합니다.
that has the pod, right?
파드가 있는 거 맞죠?
And then load balancer, three hops.
그리고 로드밸런서, 세 홉.
The load balancer, there's no load balancers
로드밸런서, 로드밸런서가 없습니다.
built into Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스에 내장되어 있다.
You have to have a plugin that stands one up for you.
여러분을 위한 플러그인이 있어야 합니다.
So Metal LB can be stood up and use BGP
그래서 Metal LB를 세워서 BGP를 사용할 수 있습니다.
to create, advertise a virtual IP
가상 IP를 생성하고 광고합니다.
that goes to the node port or something like that.
노드 포트 등으로 이동합니다.
You can also use things like the load balancers
로드 밸런서 같은 것을 사용할 수도 있습니다.
for your cloud providers, and F5 has one.
클라우드 제공업체를 위한 로드 밸런서를 사용할 수도 있습니다.
There's all sorts of load balancers out there
모든 종류의 로드 밸런서가 있습니다.
that will plug in, but you gotta do it, right?
연결할 수 있지만, 그래도 해야죠?
Kubernetes is not opinionated.
쿠버네티스는 독단적이지 않다.
You pick your load balancer,
로드밸런서를 선택한다,
and then when you set up your service,
그리고 서비스를 설정합니다,
it creates the event, and then if somebody wants
이벤트를 생성하고, 누군가 원하면
to do something with it, they can.
무언가를 하기를 원하면 할 수 있습니다.
In our cluster, when you create a load balancer,
우리 클러스터에서 로드밸런서를 생성하면,
it's gonna be pending.
보류 상태가 될 것이다.
You're never gonna get the external IP of the load balancer
로드밸런서의 외부 IP는 절대 얻을 수 없습니다.
because there's no plugin installed.
플러그인이 설치되지 않았기 때문입니다.
And so load balancer is three hops.
따라서 로드 밸런서는 세 홉입니다.
You hit the load balancer, which is a thing,
로드 밸런서를 건드렸군요,
a real device or a logical thing, right?
실제 장치나 논리적인 거지?
And then it hits the node port on one of the machines,
그리고 컴퓨터 중 하나의 노드 포트에 도달합니다,
and then third hop is back to the pod.
그리고 세 번째 홉은 다시 파드로 돌아간다.
So it's a hierarchy, and each one's more expensive.
계층 구조가 있고, 각 계층은 더 비싸다.
So you gotta decide what you wanna do.
그러니 뭘 할지 결정해야 해요.
Load balancers are nice because you can give them
로드밸런서가 좋은 이유는 다음과 같습니다.
a DNS name out on the internet, for example,
예를 들어 인터넷에 DNS 이름을 보낼 수 있습니다,
and you might have hardware replication of them.
하드웨어 복제가 있을 수 있습니다.
There might be like seven of them,
일곱 개 정도 있을 수 있습니다,
so if one fails, HA and all that.
그래서 하나가 실패하면, HA와 그 모든 것들.
So load balancers are good for external access too,
따라서 로드밸런서는 외부 접속에도 좋습니다,
but they're based on node ports, typically.
하지만 일반적으로 노드 포트를 기반으로 합니다.
They get into the cluster through a node port.
노드 포트를 통해 클러스터로 들어갑니다.
And then you have ingress.
그리고 침입합니다.
An ingress is a controller that runs in your cluster,
인그레스는 클러스터에서 실행되는 컨트롤러이다,
typically has a load balancer or a node port service
일반적으로 로드밸런서 또는 노드 포트 서비스를 가지고 있다.
in front of it, but the thing about an ingress controller
앞에 있지만, 인그레스 컨트롤러에 대한 것은
is what if I have five services?
다섯 개의 서비스가 있으면 어떨까요?
Do you wanna tell your iPhone developers,
아이폰 개발자들에게 말해주고 싶어요?
oh, if you want that, you connect over to here,
오, 그걸 원하면 여기로 접속하세요,
and if you want that, you connect over to here,
원하시면 여기로 연결하세요,
and then, oh, this part of the API
그리고 나서, 아, API의 이 부분입니다.
is actually hosted over here.
는 실제로 여기서 호스팅됩니다.
Not really, right?
그렇지 않나요?
Microservices shouldn't be exposed outside of the context
마이크로서비스는 컨텍스트 외부에 노출되어서는 안 된다.
within which you're developing them.
개발 중인 컨텍스트 내에서만 노출되어야 합니다.
The external API deals with different language,
외부 API가 다른 언어를 처리합니다,
different semantics, different bandwidths, right?
의미도 다르고, 대역폭도 다르죠?
The internet is flaky and low bandwidth.
인터넷이 불안정하고 대역폭이 낮습니다.
Your data center is gonna be fast and reliable.
데이터 센터는 빠르고 안정적입니다.
They're very different worlds.
아주 다른 세상입니다.
The ingress controller can create kind of like a firewall,
인그레스 컨트롤러는 방화벽과 같은 것을 만들 수 있습니다,
an adapter from the outside world to the inside world.
외부 세계와 내부 세계를 연결하는 어댑터입니다.
You could have two services or eight,
서비스가 두 개일 수도 있고 여덟 개일 수도 있습니다,
and then you could say, hey, if somebody hits slash engine,
그리고 나서 누군가 슬래시 엔진을 누르면 이렇게 말할 수 있습니다,
send them over here.
여기로 보내주세요.
If they hit slash web, send them over there.
슬래시 웹에 부딪히면 저쪽으로 보내세요.
And so an ingress controller gets rules
그래서 인그레스 컨트롤러는 규칙을 얻습니다.
that tell it how to send the traffic inside the cluster
클러스터 내부로 트래픽을 전송하는 방법을 알려준다.
to the different services that are on the inside.
내부에 있는 다른 서비스로 전송합니다.
So you might have a bunch of your little microservices
따라서 작은 마이크로서비스가 여러 개 있을 수 있습니다.
with cluster IPs only.
클러스터 IP로만.
You don't want them accessed from the outside.
외부에서 액세스하는 것을 원하지 않습니다.
And then you have an ingress controller
그리고 출입 컨트롤러가 있습니다.
that provides your public interface,
퍼블릭 인터페이스를 제공합니다,
and it sends all the traffic
그리고 모든 트래픽을 전송합니다.
to those guys behind the scenes.
배후에 있는 사람들에게요.
And it's the ingress controller
그리고 출입 컨트롤러입니다
that has a load balancer service in front of it,
그 앞에 로드밸런서 서비스가 있습니다,
and only the ingress controller.
그리고 인그레스 컨트롤러만.
It's the one way in, right?
한 방향으로만 들어오는 거죠?
So you might create node ports on the fly
그래서 노드 포트를 즉석에서 만들 수 있습니다.
to test things and to experiment if you're on the inside,
테스트하고 내부에 있는지 실험할 수 있습니다,
but the outside world never sees those.
하지만 외부 세계에서는 절대 볼 수 없다.
What's a gateway?
게이트웨이가 뭐지?
A gateway is a more powerful ingress controller.
게이트웨이는 더 강력한 인그레스 컨트롤러입니다.
Ingress is a thing in Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스에서 인그레스는 존재한다.
It's a defined framework.
정의된 프레임워크입니다.
Again, Kubernetes doesn't provide one.
다시 말하지만, 쿠버네티스는 이를 제공하지 않는다.
You have to install one,
하나를 설치해야 한다,
and we're gonna use Ambassador.
앰배서더를 사용하겠습니다.
Oops, sorry, Emissary.
죄송합니다, 사절님.
It used to be called Ambassador.
예전에는 앰배서더라고 불렸죠.
And so we're gonna use Emissary for that.
그래서 이젠 사절이라고 부르죠.
Well, guess what?
그거 알아?
Emissary does the Kubernetes ingress framework,
Emissary는 쿠버네티스 인그레스 프레임워크를 수행한다,
but Emissary is crazy powerful
하지만 Emissary는 엄청나게 강력하다.
and has tons of other features.
다른 기능도 많아요.
It can inject headers.
헤더를 주입할 수 있습니다.
It can do fault stuff for chaos operations.
카오스 연산을 위한 결함 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다.
It could do all sorts of things.
모든 종류의 일을 할 수 있습니다.
And so it's a gateway.
그래서 관문이죠.
It's a super powerful way to provide a single place
한 곳에서 제공하는 매우 강력한 방법입니다.
where all your traffic can come in.
모든 트래픽이 들어올 수 있는 곳입니다.
It can do security stuff.
보안 작업을 할 수 있습니다.
Obviously, TLS is even part of ingress,
분명히 TLS도 인그레스의 일부입니다,
but it can do some more advanced security things.
하지만 좀 더 고급 보안 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다.
So it's a very, very powerful tool.
아주 강력한 도구입니다.
So this is an example of host port,
이것이 호스트 포트의 예시입니다,
where you have host port in the pod spec
파드 스펙에 호스트 포트가 있는 경우
and then the container port.
그리고 컨테이너 포트.
And if there's no host with that port open,
그리고 해당 포트가 열려있는 호스트가 없으면,
your pod's pending forever
파드가 영원히 보류된다.
until that port is available somewhere.
해당 포트를 어딘가에서 사용할 수 있을 때까지.
So not a great thing for developers or users,
개발자나 사용자 모두에게 좋지 않습니다,
more for operators.
운영자에게는 더 좋습니다.
That's a node port.
노드 포트입니다.
You just ask for type node port,
노드 포트를 요청하면 됩니다,
and then you can ask for the port that you want,
그리고 원하는 포트를 요청하면 됩니다,
but if it's in use, you'll get an error.
하지만 사용 중이면 오류가 발생합니다.
If you leave the node port off,
노드 포트를 꺼두면
Kubernetes will assign you one from the range,
쿠버네티스가 이 범위에서 하나를 할당한다,
just like with the cluster IP, as we saw.
클러스터 IP와 마찬가지로.
And then this is a load balancer.
그리고 이것은 로드밸런서입니다.
You just say type load balancer.
로드 밸런서라고 입력하면 됩니다.
That's it.
끝났습니다.
In this case, this guy has two ports,
이 경우, 이 녀석은 두 개의 포트를 가지고 있습니다,
HTTP and HTTPS, which is kind of common.
HTTP와 HTTPS, 꽤나 일반적인 포트입니다.
And then you've got ingress.
그리고 인그레스가 들어옵니다.
This is an ingress rule.
이것이 진입 규칙입니다.
This ingress rule says,
이 진입 규칙은 이렇게 말합니다,
hey, if somebody hits the ingress controller
이봐, 만약 누군가가 진입 컨트롤러를 치면
using the HTTP protocol,
HTTP 프로토콜을 사용합니다,
and by the way, ingress only supports HTTP and HTTPS,
참고로 인그레스는 HTTP와 HTTPS만 지원합니다,
and they are using the route slash engine as their prefix,
그리고 접두사로 경로 슬래시 엔진을 사용하고 있습니다,
could be anything after that,
그 이후는 무엇이든 될 수 있습니다,
then send them to the backend service called engine.
그런 다음 엔진이라는 백엔드 서비스로 보냅니다.
That's the name of the service, DNS Resolved, on port 80.
이것이 포트 80의 DNS 확인된 서비스 이름입니다.
Very simple.
아주 간단합니다.
And the developers can create these rules.
그리고 개발자는 이러한 규칙을 만들 수 있습니다.
My DevOps team can provide the deployment that runs my pods,
데브옵스 팀이 내 파드를 실행하는 배포를 제공할 수 있습니다,
the service that lets people inside the cluster
클러스터 내부의 사람들이
get to them, and the ingress rule
그리고 진입 규칙
that allows traffic from the outside to route in.
외부에서 들어오는 트래픽을 허용합니다.
Now obviously I gotta coordinate with the other people
이제 당연히 다른 사람들과 조율해야 합니다.
so we don't have overlapping routes and stuff,
경로가 겹치지 않게요,
but that's the idea, right?
하지만 그게 아이디어죠?
Let those teams be independent.
그 팀들을 독립시키자.
And then the last thing is the gateway.
그리고 마지막은 관문입니다.
This is an example of configuring a gateway.
다음은 게이트웨이를 구성하는 예제입니다.
That's a custom resource definition.
사용자 정의 리소스 정의입니다.
It's not part of Kubernetes,
쿠버네티스의 일부가 아니다,
but Kubernetes gives you the ability
하지만 쿠버네티스는 다음과 같은 기능을 제공한다.
to create your own resource definitions like this one.
를 사용하여 이와 같은 리소스 정의를 직접 생성할 수 있다.
And this one gives you the ability then
그리고 이것은 다음과 같은 기능을 제공합니다.
to do things like inject headers,
헤더 인젝션과 같은 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다,
and fancy stuff like control the maximum connections.
그리고 최대 연결 제어와 같은 멋진 것들을 할 수 있습니다.
None of that's supported in ingress,
인그레스에서는 이 중 어느 것도 지원되지 않습니다,
but emissary's super powerful
하지만 사절은 매우 강력하다
and has all these kind of advanced features,
그리고 이런 고급 기능들을 모두 가지고 있습니다,
so we would call it typically a gateway.
따라서 일반적으로 게이트웨이라고 부릅니다.
It also supports protocols
프로토콜도 지원합니다.
that the ingress controller doesn't support.
수신 컨트롤러가 지원하지 않는 프로토콜도 지원합니다.
Ingress, only HTTP and HTTPS.
인그레스, HTTP와 HTTPS만 가능합니다.
If you want SCTP or UDP, you're gonna need a gateway.
SCTP 또는 UDP를 원한다면 게이트웨이가 필요합니다.
And so lab step four walks you through installing emissary
그래서 실습 4단계에서는 엠시전 설치를 안내합니다.
and doing some ingress and some gateway stuff.
진입과 게이트웨이 작업도 해봅니다.
So you get a chance to work with the CRDs
그래서 CRD와 함께 일할 기회를 얻었습니다.
that emissary installs
그 사절단이 설치한다
and the ingress controller standard Kubernetes stuff.
그리고 인그레스 컨트롤러 표준 쿠버네티스 물건.
Why would you use ingress
왜 인그레스를 사용하는가?
if gateways are so much more powerful?
게이트웨이가 훨씬 더 강력하다면?
Well, those specs I just showed you,
방금 보여드린 사양이 그렇죠,
those custom resource definitions
그 커스텀 리소스 정의들
are emissary custom resource definitions.
은 에미시 커스텀 리소스 정의입니다.
If you later switch to something else,
나중에 다른 것으로 전환하는 경우,
they're not gonna work.
작동하지 않습니다.
But ingress is a Kubernetes framework standard.
하지만 인그레스는 쿠버네티스 프레임워크 표준이다.
It's gonna work everywhere.
어디에서나 작동할 겁니다.
The nginx ingress controller will take them.
nginx 인그레스 컨트롤러가 가져갈 것입니다.
The emissary will take them.
사절단이 가져갈 것입니다.
So if you can get away with just using ingress,
침입만으로 도망칠 수 있다면,
it's portable, right?
휴대가 가능하죠?
Not a bad thing.
나쁘지 않네.
So you have to decide what you need.
그러니 필요한 게 뭔지 결정해야지.
All right, what I'm gonna do is cover service mesh
좋아, 내가 할 일은 서비스 메시를 커버하는 거야.
because we got a little bit of time left.
시간이 조금 남았으니까요.
If you wanna start on the emissary lab, go for it.
사절단 연구소를 시작하고 싶으면 시작하세요.
But I'm gonna cover service mesh real quick.
하지만 난 서비스 메시를 빨리 다룰 거야.
And I tell you what,
그리고 이렇게 말하죠,
we'll leave these boxes up for another hour or two.
이 상자를 한두 시간 더 열어두겠습니다.
So if you didn't get through all the labs,
모든 실험실을 통과하지 못했다면,
you'll have some time there.
시간이 좀 있을 겁니다.
And then probably like after lunch,
그리고 아마 점심 식사 후에,
we'll shut them down, let's say that way.
그렇게 해서 종료하겠습니다.
So if you wanna work through lunch, you can.
점심시간까지 일하고 싶으면 그렇게 하세요.
So let's hit the service mesh stuff.
그럼 서비스 메시 작업을 시작해보죠.
Service mesh functionality.
서비스 메시 기능.
I mean, we've got all this functionality
이 모든 기능이 있습니다.
built into Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스에 내장되어 있다.
We've got the CNI, we've got services,
CNI가 있고, 서비스가 있습니다,
we've got ingress, and now these gateways.
인그레스, 그리고 이제 이 게이트웨이들.
And there's just so much power and capability
그리고 엄청난 힘과 능력이 있습니다.
from a networking standpoint.
네트워킹 관점에서 보면 말이죠.
And there is complexity,
그리고 복잡성도 있습니다,
but when you start poking around and looking at it
하지만 이리저리 뒤져보고 저리 뒤져보면
in the labs here, you realize that it's manageable.
여기 실험실에서는 관리가 가능하다는 것을 깨닫게 됩니다.
But what's left, right?
하지만 남은 건 뭐죠?
Well, if you're a developer
글쎄, 만약 당신이 개발자라면
and your boss is hammering on you about security,
상사가 보안에 대해 잔소리를 하는 경우,
security, security,
보안, 보안,
do you really want to go back and instrument
"정말 돌아가서 악기를 연주하고 싶니?
every single service you wrote with mutual TLS?
모든 서비스를 상호 TLS로 작성했나요?
And how likely are you to get that right anyway?
이걸 맞출 확률이 얼마나 될까요?
And then you're gonna be,
그리고 넌 그렇게 될 거야,
now you've got another thing to debug and to manage.
이제 디버깅하고 관리해야 할 것이 하나 더 생겼습니다.
That alone right there is a killer.
그것만으로도 살인자네.
And then as soon as you do it,
그리고 곧바로
now all your customers are broken.
이제 모든 고객이 망가졌습니다.
They gotta implement on their side, the mutual TLS stuff.
상호 TLS를 구현해야 합니다.
That's a pain in Java or C++ or Go or Rust or whatever.
자바나 C++, 고, 러스트 등에서는 골치 아픈 일이죠.
Well, wouldn't it be amazing
글쎄, 정말 놀랍지 않겠어?
if you could just flip a switch
스위치 하나만 돌릴 수 있다면
and inject a proxy into every pod
모든 파드에 프록시를 주입한다.
that did the mutual TLS automatically
상호 TLS를 자동으로 수행했다.
for every single outbound connection
모든 단일 아웃바운드 연결에 대해
and on the other side for everything that comes in?
그리고 반대쪽에서 들어오는 모든 연결에 대해?
That would be amazing.
정말 멋지네요.
And wouldn't it be amazing if those pods,
저 포드가 있다면 정말 놀랍지 않을까요?
so that you didn't have to, reported telemetry that says,
라는 텔레메트리를 보고했습니다,
I'm connecting at this moment in time.
지금 이 순간 연결 중입니다.
I've been connected for this period of time.
이 시간 동안 연결되었습니다.
Ooh, I'm seeing these errors come back
오, 이런 오류가 다시 나타납니다.
and just reported that all to a central repository
방금 중앙 저장소에 보고했습니다.
that you could open up in Prometheus and chart
프로메테우스에서 열어서 차트를 만들 수 있습니다.
and look at and set alerts on.
보고 알림을 설정할 수 있습니다.
That would be amazing.
대단하네요.
And that's why service meshes are amazing.
이것이 바로 서비스 메시가 놀라운 이유입니다.
Those are the things that they do.
그게 바로 그들이 하는 일입니다.
They give you MTLS for free,
그들은 당신에게 MTLS를 무료로 제공합니다,
communications metrics for free,
통신 지표를 무료로 제공합니다,
communication policy.
통신 정책.
You can't talk to that guy, but you can't talk to this guy.
저 사람과 대화할 수도 없고, 이 사람과도 대화할 수 없습니다.
And you can't talk to that guy on Friday or whatever.
그리고 금요일 같은 날에는 저 남자랑 얘기할 수 없어.
Policy.
정책.
Traces, fault injection, chaos support,
트레이스, 오류 주입, 카오스 지원,
advanced traffic management.
고급 트래픽 관리.
This is what service mesh brings to the table.
서비스 메시가 등장합니다.
And there are a bunch of them to choose from.
그리고 선택할 수 있는 여러 가지가 있습니다.
There are proxy-based service meshes.
프록시 기반 서비스 메시가 있습니다.
So this is the longstanding group, right?
이 그룹이 가장 오래된 그룹이죠?
Your linkerdys and istios and open service meshes
링커디와 이스티오, 개방형 서비스 메시가 등장합니다.
and so on and so forth.
그리고 등등.
And so those guys are well understood.
그래서 그 사람들은 잘 이해합니다.
They're also nice because they operate in the pod sphere.
그들은 또한 포드 구체에서 작동하기 때문에 좋습니다.
They're not messing around in the kernel
그들은 커널에서 장난치지 않는다.
or down at the host level.
또는 호스트 레벨에서 다운되었습니다.
And this means that the second your traffic leaves your pod,
이는 트래픽이 파드를 떠나는 순간을 의미합니다,
it's encrypted.
암호화된다.
And so that's nice, right?
멋지지 않나요?
If you're running some sensitive workloads,
민감한 워크로드를 실행하는 경우,
who are the administrators on those computers, right?
해당 컴퓨터의 관리자는 누구죠?
So there's some really nice things
그래서 정말 좋은 것들이 있습니다.
about having a proxy-based solution.
프록시 기반 솔루션에 대해
And then the other thing that's also nice about that
그리고 또 한 가지 좋은 점이 있습니다.
is that it's not in your software.
이 소프트웨어에 없다는 것입니다.
You can upgrade the proxy
프록시를 업그레이드할 수 있습니다.
without messing with your software, right?
소프트웨어를 망치지 않고도 말이죠?
They have different life cycles and stuff.
수명 주기도 다르고요.
Then you have eBPF-based.
그리고 eBPF 기반이 있습니다.
So this is a little bit bleeding edge.
이것은 약간 최첨단입니다.
There's some really awesome stuff in the hopper there,
저기 호퍼에 정말 멋진 물건이 있네요,
but there's some downsides too.
하지만 몇 가지 단점도 있습니다.
And the biggest thing is that I don't think
그리고 가장 큰 것은 제가 생각하기에
you're gonna see a lot of GA eBPF service mesh
많은 GA eBPF 서비스 메시를 보게 될 것입니다.
implementations at this moment, soon,
곧 구현될 예정입니다,
but it's a little early days there.
하지만 아직은 조금 이른 시기입니다.
Cilium, for example, and others can provide
예를 들어 실리움 등은
that kind of functionality.
그런 종류의 기능을 제공합니다.
And then library-based.
그리고 라이브러리 기반.
What if you're using gRPC everywhere?
모든 곳에서 gRPC를 사용한다면 어떨까요?
Well, gRPC could do the TLS for you.
gRPC가 TLS를 대신 해줄 수 있습니다.
And it's gRPC library, right?
그리고 gRPC 라이브러리 맞죠?
If you're using it on both sides,
양쪽에서 모두 사용하는 경우,
then you could flip that on.
뒤집으면 됩니다.
And gRPC just, I think, went GA
그리고 gRPC는 그냥 GA가 된 것 같아요.
with their proxy-less service mesh.
프록시 없는 서비스 메시로.
And so you could use the control plane
그래서 컨트롤 플레인을 사용할 수 있습니다.
of a standard service mesh to talk to your gRPC libraries
표준 서비스 메시를 사용하여 gRPC 라이브러리와 통신할 수 있습니다.
and tell them to do what they need to do
필요한 작업을 수행하도록 지시합니다.
to do the service mesh stuff.
서비스 메시 작업을 수행합니다.
And now you don't have a proxy.
이제 프록시가 없습니다.
So the proxy does add some latency, right?
프록시 때문에 지연 시간이 늘어난 거죠?
So that's why the people who build their proxies
그래서 프록시를 구축하는 사람들이
build them to be crazy fast.
엄청나게 빠르게 구축합니다.
And then the linkerd, which is what we're gonna use,
그리고 링커드를 사용할 것입니다,
is super awesome and has a Rust-based proxy.
은 정말 멋지고 Rust 기반 프록시가 있습니다.
So compiled down to super compact, fast, native code.
따라서 매우 작고 빠른 네이티브 코드로 컴파일됩니다.
And linkerd's kind of famous for being the fastest
그리고 링커드는 가장 빠른 것으로 유명합니다.
of the proxy-based service meshes out there.
프록시 기반 서비스 메시 중 가장 빠른 것으로 유명합니다.
And it's also super easy to install and works really great.
또한 설치가 매우 쉽고 정말 훌륭하게 작동합니다.
So the last lab, which I know there's no slide,
마지막 실험실은 슬라이드가 없는 것으로 알고 있습니다,
lab five, is gonna have you install linkerd
5번 실험실에서는 링커드를 설치해야 합니다.
and then start looking at some of the metrics,
그리고 몇 가지 메트릭을 살펴봅니다,
how you can see connections
연결을 보는 방법
and see them that they're secured.
보안이 설정되어 있는지 확인합니다.
It's really an amazing thing to see
정말 놀라운 일입니다.
and it's so easy to try out.
시도하기 너무 쉬워요.
So one of the shorter lab steps.
실험실 단계가 짧아졌습니다.
So what I am going to do is say thank you a ton for coming.
와주셔서 정말 감사하다는 말씀을 드리고 싶습니다.
We do have another few minutes if you wanna hang out
더 놀고 싶으시면 몇 분 더 있습니다.
to the bottom of the hour,
한 시간 남았습니다,
but I think they will kick us out in like three minutes.
3분 안에 쫓겨날 것 같아요.
So feel free to keep working on the lab up until the last
그러니 마지막까지 실험실에서 계속 일하세요.
if you want to, or work on it for lunch.
원한다면 점심시간에 작업해도 됩니다.
We'll leave the boxes up for a bit.
잠시 상자를 열어두겠습니다.
And yeah, thanks a bunch for coming.
네, 와주셔서 감사합니다.
Have a wonderful rest of your convention.
남은 컨벤션도 즐겁게 보내세요.
Thank you.
감사합니다.